<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe relation of the present troubles in England: vvritten from London the 22. of Ianuary 1644. to a minister of one of the reformed churches in France. VVherein, is clearely set downe who are the authours of them, and whereto the innovations both in church and state there doe tend. Faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
            <title>Letter concerning the present troubles in England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E303_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861093</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E303[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe relation of the present troubles in England: vvritten from London the 22. of Ianuary 1644. to a minister of one of the reformed churches in France. VVherein, is clearely set downe who are the authours of them, and whereto the innovations both in church and state there doe tend. Faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
                  <title>Letter concerning the present troubles in England.</title>
                  <author>Tully, T. (Thomas), 1620-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hall printer to the Universitie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Consists of "A letter concerning the present troubles in England" (Wing L1354) with added title page. All reported copies retain the original title page.</note>
                  <note>"There is no doubt that the translator (or possibly writer) was Thomas Tully"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: London, Jan. 22. 1644.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE RELATION OF the preſent Troubles in ENGLAND:</p>
            <p>VVritten from LONDON the 22. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1644 to a Miniſter of one of the Reformed Churches in FRANCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherein,</hi> Is clearely ſet downe who are the Authours of them, and whereto the Innovations both in Church and State there doe tend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by HENRY HALL Printer to the UNIVERSITIE. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113221:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113221:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER CONCERNING the preſent Troubles in ENGLAND:</p>
            <p>VVritten from LONDON the 22. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1644. to a Miniſter of one of the Reformed Churches in FRANCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherein,</hi> Is clearly ſet downe who are the Authours of them, and whereto the Innovations both in Church and State there do tend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated out of the</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by HENRY HALL Printer to the UNIVERSITIE. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113221:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113221:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O ſooner did this Letter fall into my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands, but ſtraight I had a thought to publiſh it; to the end that all the world might be acquainted with the deportment of that Faction in <hi>England,</hi> which for theſe three or foure yeares together hath cauſed the effuſion of ſo much blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d there. Some hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily of our religion in <hi>France</hi> will at firſt glance diſreliſh my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne: but after they have throughly weighed it, I am confident they will all joyntly acknowledge their engagements to me for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them with a worke which undeceives their credulity, who ſtrongly fancy that we countenance <hi>their</hi> irregular proceedings, and meet in the ſame thoughts with thoſe that have beene the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy contrivers of them. And it may be alſo that ſome among the Catholiques will be ready to ſay this is but the opinion meerely of ſome one particular Perſon, and that all Proteſtants will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto it. But I proteſt before God, that I never heard of any knowing judicious man with us, whoſe diſcourſe agrees not with that of the Author here; and it were to be wiſhed that the whole world would conforme it ſelfe to the example of the <hi>Reformed</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> Were it ſo, there ſhould no Prince ſtand in need of guards, or be forced to levy Armies for the defence of his Perſon againſt the inſolence and Rebellion of Subjects. There would be no more undermining the peace of the Church, which would now cheriſh a compleat union &amp; abſolute correſpondency betwixt its owne and the ſecular government, confining it ſelfe to its proper limits, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill a ſpeciall regard to that ſubordination which is required of it. I ſpeake this, Reader, becauſe it is true; though ſundry conceive otherwiſe of it, either meerely out of a cuſtome they have embraced wholly to ſurrender themſelves unto the ſway of other mens judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: or becauſe they have a ſtrong prejudice againſt the Diſcipline we practice, as if it were not altogether ſo agreeable with Monarchy. Iudge of it by the grounds thereof, and pauſe a while in comparing our actions with our doctrine (without reſting upon any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration)
<pb facs="tcp:113221:4"/> and thou canſt not but conclude, that the ſole drift of our intentions hath ever beene to defend our ſelves rather by the weapons of the Spirit, then thoſe of the fleſh, and that we joine in an unanimous deteſtation of all ſuch as maintaine it lawfull to make uſe of temporall violence for promoting the truth of the Goſpell. This Letter I here preſent thee with, is caſt in the mould of the true Proteſtants. It appeares in defence of their doctrine touching the power of Kings, and the obedience of Subjects; withall condemning their proceedings, who under a pretence of purging the Church from its errours and enormities, and reinſtating Chriſtians in their loſt Liberty, maske a deſigne of engaging the whole world in a horrible confuſion. I cannot informe thee, who is the author of it. Thus much only thou maieſt know, that ſojourning in England, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Miniſter, (a freind of his, and a man of great abilities) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted of him a large account in writing of the preſent diſtempers there. He hath done it, thou ſeeſt. He paints them in their proper colours, points out the contrivers of them, and their aimes. He makes it legible to the world, that this Parliament is nothing, in generality, but a ſeditious Crew, bending all their indeavours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lawes of the Realme, with a deſigne to turne all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turvy; nor this Synod but (for the greateſt part alſo) an Aſſembly of Heretiques and Ignoramuſſes, that trample upon all the max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes of Chriſtianity, and entertaine no thoughts, but of an Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall confuſion. That the People (in groſſe) are wholly ſet upon Anarchy, being coſened by a conſent wrought in them by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament touching the Tyranny (as they phraſe it) of Kings; and intoxicated by the Synod with the hopes of a moſt bleſſed condition, were they but once freed from that inſupportable yoake of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. If happily out of this throng God hath ſequeſtred ſome well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected perſons for himſelfe, they are ſo thinne a company, that they dare not declare themſelves, for feare of being overborne by the malice and number of the reſt, as divers have already beene. Weigh by this, Reader, if the malady be not great, the remedy diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113221:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER CONCERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent troubles in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had the Honour to give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in writing of my abode here in <hi>England,</hi> I had not the leaſt intention to acquaint you with all my thoughs touching the preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers of the ſame. Not that the feare of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cenſure could amate me, although I am not ignorant, that he who would give a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full indifferent relation thereof, muſt oppoſe himſelfe to thoſe ordinary impreſſions, which men have already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained concerning them. And if this amuſe them (as no doubt but it will) that I cannot prevaile with my ſelfe to nouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e them on in an errour, whereinto the malice or ignorance of their miſinformers hath ſo deeply plunged them, I ſhall for a long time runne the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their disfavour, as being reſolved not to write any thing but of what I have beene an eye-witneſſe, and which you will finde to beare no great harmony with the common voice. It is undoubtedly a matter of no triviall concernment to provide that the world be herein diſabuſed, and that the truth of a buſineſſe of this nature be no longer liable to miſapprehenſion. Wherein you are ſomewhat inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed your ſelfe by that common profeſſion you make in the liſt of ſuch conſcientious Perſons as are deſigned to ſuperintend the good of People, and to ſteere their Conſciences aright. And I hope you (with many moe beſides) will not be wanting to give the world ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction what a diſparity you conceive betwixt the proceedings of
<pb facs="tcp:113221:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113221:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113221:6"/> moſt of theſe Novell Reformers, and of thoſe who in former ages at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to reſcue the Church from that Tyranny, under which for ſo long a time it groaned.</p>
            <p>For my part I finde ſo little conformity in theſe latter to our firſt Reformers, that I thinke it concernes them to guild over with ſome ſpecious pretext the poiſon they diffuſe, as being their Enemies, not their Followers; or if perhaps they make a ſhew of treading the ſame path, 'tis not out of any intention to joine and aſſociate with them, but rather to marre and undoe the worke which by their meanes was ſet on foote in the world. And in truth, Sir, what can be hoped for from ſuch a Rabble as this (naturally ſo inſolent and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong) but the markes of Rebellion both againſt God and Man? it being their ſole employment to advance factions and fidings, when ever the affaires either of Religion or Policy are brought into agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So that if you abate hence all who have, either (out of haughtines and unbridledneſſe of Spirit) combined againſt their Prince, or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed the Schiſmes and ruptures of the Church in broaching their empty and wild Fancies, I dare not promiſe that the reſidue ſhall afford you either a Body of Subjects, or a Congregation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            <p>I intend not to diſcourſe of thoſe of the King's Party; wherein ('tis true) there be ſome apparently culpable, but yet more of ſuch as I may call really unfortunate, thoſe alone I meane, that make up the greateſt number of Reformed and Honeſt men in that Kingdome. I ſhall confine my Diſcourſe to thoſe, who beare the World in hand, they are at oddes with nothing but Popery, which in their jealous apprehenſions was taking roote in <hi>England</hi> againe. With this pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cheate they have got the approbation of not a few Proteſtants, who (without ſifting their deſigne) are by this meanes engaged to applaude a pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icidiall attempt upon the Soveraigne Majeſty, and a villainous plot againſt the Sacred <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the Church. Either of which two crimes is doubtleſſe one of the moſt eſſentiall notes of reprobation; nor is it poſſible for him to make good the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, who complies or holds any the leaſt correſpondence with ſuch as are knowingly guilty of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Your new-fangled Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> are moſtly involved in the equall guilt of both. For who knowes not how at the very firſt riſe of theſe troubles they preached openly to the People, That <hi>Kings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113221:6"/> are not to be obeyed if once they aſſault their Liberties and Priviledges</hi> (which in their conſtruction is the firſt ſteppe to Tyranny) <hi>or taking upon them to intermeddle in Church affaires, they fall upon any abſurd &amp; impious opinion.</hi> Wherein they came nothing ſhort of Cardinall <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> who writes, <hi>That if Princes ſhall once apply themſelves to the protection of Hereſy or exerciſe of Tyranny, they are left to the mercy of the Pope, and the Church, who are firſt to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them, then to abſolve the Subjects from the Oath of Allegiance, and they upon this diſcharge, aſſoone as they can be provided of a competent ſtrength are to employ it againſt them, to expoſe them to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and by all meanes feiſible to dethrone them.</hi> A wonderfull thing that they who are ſuch profeſſed enemies to the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> that uſe their perſons (when they ſeize them) with ſo much inhumani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for the continued revolution of ſo many yeares have expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their bodies quartered to all paſſengers (as a ſpectacle of horrour) upon their moſt eminent Gates, ſhould notwithſtanding ſhake hands with them in a point for the which at firſt they did ſo much abhorre them. Would you not conclude that they are all alike the Diſciples of <hi>Mariana,</hi> and the Agents of a <hi>Boniface?</hi> what affinity is there betwixt theſe Doctours and Saint <hi>Ambroſe?</hi> when this great Saint, this reall Chriſtian perceived that the <hi>Arians</hi> were about to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe themſelves of the Church in <hi>Milan,</hi> with the approbation of the Emperour <hi>Valentinian,</hi> he addreſſed himſelfe unto that Prince in theſe tearmes; <hi>Royall Sir, we intreate, we preſume not to fight. If the Prince will needs make uſe of his Supreame power, I am ready to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the duty of a Prelate. I ſhall ſtand upon my defence, but 'tis in the petitions of the poore. I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emoane me, I can weepe, I can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh; but againſt Armes, againſt Souldiers, againſt the Gothes, my onely wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are teares, nor ought I to uſe any other manner of reſiſtance what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</hi> And in another place, <hi>If the Kingdome ſhall lye panting under the preſſures of Tyranny, I am ready to ſuffer any kind of violence, even Death it ſelfe.</hi> Beſides that univerſall injunction laid upon Chriſtians, <hi>to put up injuries with patience, (God having reſerved unto himſelfe the right of revenging by the power of his Juſtice,</hi> as Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> upon <hi>Job</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Man being uncapable of performing it, but with a heart fraught with malice)</hi> he knew I ſay beſides this what <hi>David</hi> once ſung to God; <hi>againſt thee onely have I ſinned:</hi> upon which paſſage (in the Apology he compiled for him) he thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113221:7"/> 
               <hi>He was a King, and ſo not within the reach of the Lawes: Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis delictorum liberi ſunt reges;</hi> if I may borrow the atteſtation of ſo divine a pen. Now if <hi>David</hi> were not miſtaken, if Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpake reaſon in this point, with Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who aſſures us ſo punctually, that <hi>Kings are above the Lawes;</hi> What ſhall we thinke of our upſtart <hi>Reformers,</hi> that have placed Kings below their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſtirre up the People againſt their Kings? It is a pregnant evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they are ſwayed by that ſpirit of rebellion, which heretofore animated the <hi>Gregories,</hi> the <hi>Bonifaces,</hi> the <hi>Mariana's,</hi> the <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi> to attempt upon the Honour and life of Kings, rather then by that ſpirit of wiſedome and meekeneſſe, which moved <hi>Solomon</hi> to leave this divine precept behind him, (equally obliging all that have not forfeited their reaſon) never to divorce the reſpect due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Kings from that which they owe unto God himſelfe; and in caſe they ſhall preſume to do otherwiſe, aſſociating themſelves with ſuch Libertines as refuſe to pay the tribute of obedience, to be afraid their calamity doe not ariſe ſuddainly. The Pulpits here are full of none but Preachers of diſcord and diviſion betwixt the King and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. In lieu of praiſes, magnifying the name of God, Invocation of the Holy Spirit, Confeſſion of Sinnes, ſighs and groanes for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion thereof, here is nothing to be heard but reproaches, revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and accuſations. Charity in all other places throwes her skirt over the Errours ſhe diſcovers, be they as great and numerous as can be. 'Tis charity here to lay them naked in the view of the world, and if there be no reall ones, to deviſe ſome, that ſo they may never be deſtitute of a forgery wherewith to traduce their Prince. His Perſon and Actions are both expoſed to publique reproaches: The Churches Ring of nothing but declamations againſt Him; and if happily ſome ſmall relickes of ſhame have ever ſlacked the heate of thoſe bawling <hi>Predicants,</hi> or railing <hi>Scriblers,</hi> impudence makes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in compenſation to double the Cry. This yet is nothing in compariſon of their uſuall Execrations, as if that Law pronounced by the mouth of God himſelfe, which forbids <hi>to curſe the Prince of his People, no not ſo much as in thought,</hi> did not at all concerne them. That deteſtable <hi>League</hi> which in the memory of our Fathers was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuch tragique effects in three or foure of our Kings raignes, and againſt which our Proteſtants have alwaies ſo eagerly declaimed, laying their grounds upon certaine proofes drawne from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113221:7"/> the corruption of <hi>Rome,</hi> which gave life unto it, had nothing in it of more venimous conſequence, then this we ſee here, ſave that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries and Boute-feus of the Engliſh Confederacy have not as yet imbrued their hands in the bloud of their King.</p>
            <p>And can it ſuite with their profeſſion, who talke ſo much of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Chriſtian Religion to it's primitive purity, and reviving the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Simplicity of the Apoſtolique times, who call him their Maſter that reconciled the world to God, and united men in the ſame mutuall affections, who are not ignorant that Peace and Concord are the eſſentiall characters of a Chriſtian, and that ſuch ſhould never be the occaſioners of warre, to employ the ſword in ſuch a manner as this?</p>
            <p>I cannot thinke there's any man ſo credulous as to beleive, that ſuch courſes can finde any welcome among thoſe that are Proteſtants indeed; they may with many who are ſuch in ſhew onely, of which ſort are all the oppoſers, not of monarchy alone, but indefinitely of any ſecular authority whatſoever. There were ſome in the infancy of the Church, who ſtrained Chriſtian liberty ſo farre, that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it as unjuſt for the <hi>Enfranchiſed</hi> of God, and ſuch as were guided by his ſpirit, to be ſubject to the command of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> ſucked the ſame poiſon from them, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards diffuſed it ſelfe among the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> and in fine reached us alſo, by meanes of ſome who gave a ſecond birth to this Hereſy, which now walkes up and downe here in great bravery, under pretences very ſpecious in the apprehenſion of ſome ſhallow Judgements. And though I conceive this will not be to the generall prejudice of the Reformed Churches in <hi>Europe</hi> (by reaſon of that juſt jealouſy which Princes ought to entertaine, that they hold no intelligence amongſt themſelves, and that they doe not all bandy togethr againſt the rights and prerogatives of their reſpective dominions.) Yet it muſt needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to their ſhame atleaſt, if they doe not openly declare againſt the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany of their proceedings, and the iniquity of their deſignes; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince they have had the impudence to invite them to an imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their example, and to ſteppe in for the ſupport of their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I am not ignorant what grounds we goe upon, and how little reſemblance ours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare to theirs; but the world will not paſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon us by our poſitions, but either by our actions or by our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113221:8"/> For if we be ſilent when they are bragging of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with us, and yet appearing in the field againſt their Soverai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, who will not be ready to conclude that had we the like power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our hands, we would do as much every w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>it our ſelves<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the contrary we ſpeake our mindes, condemning the unlawfullneſſe and horridneſſe of their deſigne, (our actions ſuiting ſtill with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doctrine) in ſtead of exaſperating the ſecular powers, we ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them: for it cannot be but they will take part with us, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> off ſuch as make them ſo ſubordinate either to the people in gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, or to ſome ſelect parcell of the whole body, who (let them talke what they will) are no leſſe Subjects then the reſt. In breife, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> need but demand whether of the two are the better Chriſtians; thoſe that waſt ſo much bloud to ſubvert the right of Kings, and to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh a warre (under counterfeit pretences) for the ſuppreſſion of all order, and engaging the whole world to the ſame common confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Or they of the Primitive times, who maintained, <hi>that to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> bloud was to violate Chriſtianity; to oppoſe Kings, was to diſobey God, and to conteſt with Superiours, was to fight againſt that Order, which he eſtabliſhed.</hi> I beleeve they will hardly be ſwayed by examples, leſſe by reaſon; nor that they put any great value upon the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which the practiſe of the firſt ages may challenge over us. If they do, I would exhort ſuch preachers of fire and ſword, to call to minde how the ancient diſciplien of the Church denied their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion <hi>to ſuch as had ſlaine an Enemy in a lawfull warre,</hi> and that they would hence collect how thoſe times ſtood affected to ſuch as voluntarily embroyled themſelves in an unlawfull and unjuſt one.</p>
            <p>See, Sir, in part what I have to ſay to you upon this argument. It will not be amiſſe, if in the next place I acquaint you with the innovations they make in Religion, and what fruits Chriſtianity is like to reape from the labours of ſuch doughty Reformers. 'Tis a truly impious deſigne to per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue a Reformation in ſuch manner as theſe men do, and which tends onely to the ſubverſion of an order eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by God, under a pretence of pulling downe one deviſed by man, which they call <hi>Tyranny,</hi> becauſe indeed it is the onely meanes whereby to check them in that full ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of unbridled licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, unto which they are naturally ſo much devo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. Not but that there is alwayes matter enough for a reformation both in manners and government, and that it is extreamely neceſſary to correct the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113221:8"/> evills and diſorders of the preſent times, and withall to prevent that corruption which may be feared from the future. But who will be the fitteſt to go through with this taske? will the Parliament? no, in as much as the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that is the Clergy are no longer a part of it. Will the <hi>Synod</hi> be able to ſupply this defect? no, not they, becauſe the whole body is compoſed of perſons intereſſed; beſides that ignorance and blindeneſſe are there (for the moſt part) in their greateſt exaltation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or if perhaps there be ſome knowing, there is a great dearth of honeſt men, moſt of them being poſſeſt with the ſpirit of diviſion, which hath drawne them into the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paths of Hereticks, as well ancient, as moderne. Well then, ſhall the People beare the burthen? this is altogether impoſſible, unleſſe firſt there be made an univerſall reſignation of all ſence and reaſon, becauſe (of themſelves) they are uncapable of all manner of order and conduct. Neither can the King, aſſiſted only by his Counſell and Magiſtrates, be thought a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it inſtrument to mannage the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for feare he make Religion waite upon his owne private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and by conſequent bring the ſpirit under the command of the Fleſh. The iſſue then will be to finde out a juſt and lawfull way for the advancing of this Reformation; which in my opinion can be no other then that of a generall <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> indicted by the Prince; wherein the <hi>Boroughs</hi> ſhall have their Deputies, whoſe voices are to be heard, and their ſuffrages admitted; The Church it's Biſhops and Doctors; The Parliament diverſe of the Nobility, which they may chuſe out of their ſeverall Houſes; and the King his principall Officers. And to make the action more Authentique to eſtabliſh in the Church that uniformity, which ought to be in a body in which the Spirit of Union and Concord is the Moderatour (as that of Chriſtians is) there may be called thither the moſt eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants from forraigne parts, by whoſe aſſiſtance all doubts and ſcruples may be ſolved. This in my judgement is the way, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſeverall rights of each order in the State of <hi>England,</hi> as alſo in the whole body of Chriſtendome, entire. I know none that can diſlike the project, but your new <hi>Independants,</hi> and the fanatique <hi>Illuminat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> commonly called <hi>Browniſts,</hi> who in truth are no other but the Brats or Brethren of the <hi>Munſter-Faction.</hi> Theſe men have fancied to themſelves a monſtrous Common-wealth, an abſurd and motley State, in which there ſhould not be the leaſt cognizance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113221:9"/> of civill Authority, nor any other ſpirituall power acknowledged, but ſuch as the Sonne of God ſhould by an inſenſible and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence exerciſe over them. Collect now from theſe Premiſes, how ſuch kinde of people ſtand affected to Royalty, and then what reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning they make of Councels, and the Perſons they conſiſt of. Their aime indeed is to ruine both; to have no Rulers or Overſeers at all, either Temporall or Spirituall, Secular or Eccleſiaſticall. They want no ſpecious colours to blanch the blackneſſe of their Deſigne. They make their King a Demy-Apoſtate, and little better then a Tyrant: They proclaime to the world, that he <hi>had a reſolution to violate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to deſtroy their Liberties and Priviledges. That he hath ſupplanted the Fundamentall Lawes of the Realme, and falſified the Oath made to his Subjects, the obſervation of which alone muſt entitle him to a Dominion over them.</hi> As for the Overſeers of the Church, <hi>it hath no need</hi> (ſay they) <hi>of any at all, in as much as the Founder and Head thereof hath skill enough to governe, as he had to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it. That 'tis enough if there be meere Paſtours only to preach, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being lifted above others, or others above them.</hi> Such be the Authors and Abettours of this Fancie who gave the firſt blow at <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> A ſtrange thing that ſome even of the honeſter ſort, ſhould ſo raſhly mingle with the enemies of that Order, tranſported in the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their hearts by this groundleſſe conceit, that 'tis the Prelates alone who have opened the gap to wickedneſſe in the Church, as if where there are no Biſhops at all, Innocence and purity bare an abſolute and ſoveraigne command in the Soules of men. <hi>Ferrier, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes,</hi> with many more beſides in <hi>France</hi> will be perpetuall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtours to the world, that your Church Government lyes no leſſe open to the aſſaults and ſtratagems of the Devill, then that which hath beene ſetled from all Antiquity. Were it my drift to ſearch it to the bottome, it would be eaſie to demonſtrate this with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and that had it beene a few yeares elder, and liv'd in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where the Lawes of the Prince are not ſo rigorous againſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatours, as they be in <hi>France</hi> (which permits but two ſorts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) or at leaſt if God had not from time to time raiſed ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently guifted Perſons therein, (in which reſpect I muſt needs confidently affirme, that it flouriſheth now more then ever) there could not have wanted matter, through the many viſible inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences thereof, to embroyle the Church in a tedious and perpetuall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113221:9"/> taske. I ſhall but point at one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'tis the equality of Paſtours, which indeed at firſt bluſh preſents you with a comely gloſſe, and hath a wonderfull influence upon the fancy, when it beholds it at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but (in truth) is the ſource of diſorder, the fountaine of negligence, and the bane of that laudable emulation among the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous to out-ſtrip one another in goodneſſe. It is to ſhut the doore againſt the perfection of life, in denying the ſtricteſt obſervers of their maſters injunctions thoſe advantages and prerogatives which himſelfe hath deſigned them. What a block is it in the way to all thoſe eminent perſons without, who were a coming toward us? You know better then I how memorable to this purpoſe is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>the Arch-biſhop of Spalata?</hi> Being to be honoured with no ranke at all above others, can you thinke they will quit that which they enjoy where they are? There can be no humility ſo great but may juſtly take offence at this. How can any Genius, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted thoroughly with it ſelfe, and borne to a preheminence over others with ſome ſingular endowments of Nature, be allured o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to a profeſſion, whoſe ſweeteſt bai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is but a voice with the meaneſt, and where its reſolutions ſhall be valued as cheape as thoſe of any other particular Perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The world is not to learne what a traine of inconveniencies attend theſe kind of ſuffrages and Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and how there muſt needes follow many farre worſe upon the neck of thoſe, ſo long as there is nothing but a ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſupputation of Votes, without any endowed with Power and Abilities to poyſe them. Put caſe their Aſſemblies conſiſt of a hundred Perſons; will there in truth be found ten, who will not rather be opinionate to cover their ſeverall defects, then be conformable to the example of their fellowes, or endeavour to better themſelves by their Counſells? Such is that ſelfe-love and radicall inclination we have to ſooth our ſelves, that we do not eaſily hearken to the commands of reaſon, till we be awed thereunto. And ſeeing this diſtinction of degrees is ſo neceſſary for the good of the Church, how ſhall that end be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, if there be not ſome delegated both in and out of thoſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, to repreſent the power of the whole, to exact upon all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencies an account of their proceedings, to have the right of propoſing, and collecting Votes, of ratifying Decrees, of promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating and putting them in execution, and daring to the field what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever oppoſers of the ſame? Is this feiſible without a Biſhop, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113221:10"/> that in ſuch Synods as ours all enjoy an equality of Power and Authority, and where (according to that proverbiall cenſure of the Aſſemblies of <hi>Carthage.) The greater number carries it from the better?</hi> Beſides, when the Synod is diſſolved, each Miniſter is left to his owne liberty, to do what his fancy ſhall ſuggeſt unto him. Put caſe he be found hipping either in manners or Doctrine, he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accountable to none but thoſe of his owne Conſiſtory, who are all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in readineſſe, like ſo many rotten Pillars, to ſupport a crazie Wall; or ſo many blinde guides, that will needes undertake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſtraglers into the way, or ſuch as leade men upon a praecipice. So that by this meanes the offender wants no invitations nor advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igle thoſe that lend an care to him, he being no way accountable but to another Aſſembly. In the interim he is proling for parties to his crimes, and Abettours to his Opinions; ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of fearing the rigour of a Judge in the Synod, he is often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of an Advocate, which would be altogether impoſſible were there one enabled to ſtifle ſuch diſorders in the wombe. This hints me of what I have read in <hi>Calvin</hi> upon this Argument. That <hi>the Preſbyters,</hi> to wit, all ſuch as had the cure of Soules, <hi>were accuſtomed in every City to cull out one amongſt the reſt, upon whom in particular they beſtowed the title of Biſhop, to prevent</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thoſe ordinary Diviſions, which flow from a Parity. Notwithſtanding this Biſhop was not ſo farre li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted up above his fellowes in honour and degree, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he might exerciſe any act of juriſdiction over them. His proper function reſembled that of a Conſul in the Senate. He made relation of proceedings in a full Houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e adviſed, informed, exhorted: He ruled a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by his authority, managed the whole Action, and put the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and unanimous reſults of the Senate in execution,</hi> whereto he ſubjoyneth, <hi>that according to the univerſall atteſtation of all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, the neceſſity of the times was the firſt Authoriſer of this Cuſtome.</hi> Now this neceſſity was nothing but thoſe diviſions which crept in among the Paſtours of the Church for want of ſome principall O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers, which is now farre greater in this Nation, then ever it was with them, as you ſhall ſee anon.</p>
            <p>But let us feele a little more the pulſes of theſe men that will have no degrees or preheminence in the Church. They be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame that would have none in the State alſo: They ſtrike at E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy for the ſame ends they have aſſaulted Royalty. They are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113221:10"/> no ſtrangers to the frowardneſſe of their owne diſpoſitions, but are ſufficiently convicted how farre each of them in particular hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated from the <hi>Maximes,</hi> and even from the very graine of their Anceſtours. That they are generally odious and deſtructive to the Publike, nor can ever build any hopes to themſelves but ſuch as muſt have their foundation in perpetuall diſcords. That ſeeing their expectations fruſtrate, and themſelves conſequently in a wretched condition, their onely way is to advance a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and ſo to involve all order and conſtitution of former ages (which croſſe their wicked inclinations) in the ſame common ruine. The very complexion of theſe <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ells</hi> ſpeakes the worth of what they oppoſe ſo eagerly. To which if you add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the manner how they have from the beginning invaded it, with what violence they have proceeded, you may eaſily inferre the baſeneſſe of thoſe who put them upon that employment. No ſooner had they notice of thoſe jealo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſies betwixt the King and his Parliament (wherein at that time there were not a few ſicke of the ſame diſeaſe with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) but they readily embraced the opportunity, to make their Soveraigne and the Biſhops ſenſible of their inveterate ſpleene to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. Having firſt ſet ſome of the other ſexe a worke, (which in the open ſtreets renounced all ſhame and modeſty, in lieu of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions (wherewith the cuſtome was to greet Princes) to belch out with a deliberate impudence moſt traiterous expreſſions againſt their King: the impunity of that ſexe (whoſe inſolence is oftner ſleighted, then puniſhed) animated the other to a deſperate reſolution of offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violence unto his Perſon. To which purpoſe they inveſt his Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, ſeize upon <hi>White hall</hi> gates, and had not the well mannaged providence of ſome of the <hi>Lords</hi> (though ſtrongly ſuſpected by that frantique multitude) quaſhed their deſigne, he could not have eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their hands. The King having given them the ſlip, immediately they divert the ſtreame of their fury upon the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> &amp; as if they had beene of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> deſcent, and ſome <hi>Pilates</hi> were upon the bench to give judgement, they cryed, away with thoſe followers of Chriſt, as the other had cryed, away with Chriſt himſelfe. The Parliament indeavouring in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rudent way to ſettle this diſorder, found a rub at the firſt from ſome among themſelves that had a maine hand in the buſineſſe, giving private intelligence to that ſeditio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Rabble, how their proceedings were diſliked, and how the Houſe of Lords had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113221:11"/> carried the matter in favour of the Biſhops, and that they likewiſe were ſeconded by a conſiderable party of the Houſe of Commons. This ſet them all on fire in a moment; inſomuch that of Accuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s and Proſecuters they had turned Executioners, if thoſe pious men had not by keeping out of the way given place to their fury. In the meane time they are ſtill urgent, they bawle, they threaten. But perceiving how that great Body would hardly be forced without deſtroying it, and throwing themſelves alſo into danger, they joine ſubtilty to open violence. The Biſhops muſt be impeached of High Treaſon againſt King and Kingdome, and of ſubverting the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of the Land. This prodigrous calumny nouriſhed the boldneſſe of their Abettours in Parliament, and drew over to them all the faint hearted, debarred the liberty of protecting juſtice, and rendring her venerable to ſuch as had yet freely withſtood thoſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent courſes. From that very houre they are interdicted all reſort to Parliament. Their Houſes are plundered, their perſons impriſoned, their complaints derided. In a word, there is not any outrage ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable which they did not exerciſe upon them; inſomuch that the very reaſons they alleadged to cleare themſelves, were brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the compaſſe of a high miſdemeanour, albeit they knew not how to proceed againſt them; For even in their greateſt heare they were forced to leave the matter undecided, and ſo it continues to this day. They are never more gravelled, then when they fall upon debate of that. The Parliament, that is to ſay, the <hi>Lower Houſe,</hi> and the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod,</hi> doe both joine heads together to put an end to the Queſtion. The one, in debarting thoſe a place in their Aſſembly, who have a light to ſit there from the firſt inſtitution of Parliaments, and whoſe votes in that place are ſo fundamentally neceſſary, that without them all the decrees of the other are null, and the originall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kingdomes infringed thereby. The other, contributes to their totall extirpation, and to ſhake off all obedience to them, that ſo they may open a gappe to their Libertiniſme, and force upon the Church that diſorder and confuſion which the ſpirit of giddineſſe, they are poſſeſſed with, hath ever aimed at.</p>
            <p>Judge, Sir, by theſe proceedings what ſincerity there it in theſe <hi>Noveliſts,</hi> and if any honeſt man can ſhake hands with them.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the Biſhops had indeed tranſgreſſed in matter of State, this is but a poore plea for the proſcription of Epiſcopacy in ſelfe.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113221:11"/> The Perſons ſhould be puniſhed, not the Profeſſion aboliſhed; after the example of thoſe Emperours, who having upon good ground, (ſuch at leaſt as appeared ſo to them) ejected certaine of their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, did forthwith ſubſtitute others in their roomes, to let the world know, that if with one hand they put the law in execution againſt the crimes of men, with the tother they would ſtill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the reverence due unto an Order in their eſteeme ſo ſacred, that thoſe they had diveſted of it, they adjudged altogether unworthy of the ſame. Suppoſe now they were found peccant in point of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; this they may be as Men, and as Sinners, not as Biſhops.</p>
            <p>The Miniſtery among us was never arraigned for thoſe ſtrange crimes, which have beene proved upon ſome of it's Profeſſours. The Church is here to employ her authority, which ſtretcheth not beyond ſuſpenſion or deprivation, and that of the Perſons, not of the Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How many Biſhops hath Antiquity beheld ſhameleſly profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holineſſe of their Profeſſion? How many tainted with ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, ambition, tyranny, hereſie, ſorcety? and yet never man ſaw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſiderable number of them condemned; never durſt or would any preferre a Bill for the ſuppreſſion of the Order.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant of what is here commonly objected, that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute authority and ſuperſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uity of riches are the uſuall bane of the Soule; and that there be but few men of ranke, upon whom they have not a corruptive influence. That theſe two, being as it were inſeperable Accidents, cannot be ſequeſtred from the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſtroying the Subject which containes them. That the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes</hi> concurred in the ſame judgement, and that of late they have received a totall proſcription among our ſelves.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, it is granted by all, that Riches and Authority ſuite not indeed with a narrow ſoule, uncapable either of rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, or knowingly valuing the pure and true dictates of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, who denies but there may be Biſhops without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inveſting them with an abſolute Power, or affording them any ſuch exceſſe of riches?</p>
            <p>In the whole Primitive Church there were none but indigent and neceſſitous ones, enabled with no other authority, then to diſpenſe the graces of God, and to proclaime his Judgements unto the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113221:12"/> And yet no doubt but if choice were made of conſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> men after the example of the Primitive Fathers, there would be little ground to grudge them what the bounty of Kings and the conſent of the People hath ſuffered them for ſo many ages ſucceſſively to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</p>
            <p>If they be ſuch as are indeed worthy of a Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icke, they will employ their authority in executing Juſtice upon the vicious, expend their riches in accommodating the needy, as the Prelates here doe generally at this day. Their very Adverſaries confeſſe them to have ever beene moſt ſtrict inquiſitours after crimes, and moſt ſevere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhers of the ſame. Nor can they deny, that the poore and unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, the Widowes and Orphans have ever found ſomewhat either in their Counſell or credit to protect them from ſcorne and reproach. And they muſt needs farther acknowledge, that beſides thoſe workes of Charity, (which call for a reverent eſteeme, and even a kind of veneration to the memory of an infinite traine of Biſhops) the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke monuments founded by them both for the Honour and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of that Kingdome, are ſo many pregnant arguments, that they have employed their great revenues, rather as juſt Stewards for the benefit of others, then as the vaſſals of their owne pleaſures. Witneſſe ſo many ſtately Churches, famous Colledges, rich Hoſpitals, ſo many Bridges, Foundations, Dotations, Edifices, which owe their being to that Order.</p>
            <p>'Tis true; the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes</hi> were generally againſt Biſhops: but who can give us the true meaning of thoſe we deſire may paſſe for our patternes? How many were there amongſt them whom it would be a great crime to propoſe for our imitation? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be induced to beleive, that they of the moſt rationall ſort among them, who were beſt acquainted with the Errours which had then ſtole into the Church, were the ſame with thoſe who at that time made warre upon the Biſhops. Nor can I thinke, that they who maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred <hi>Trincavell,</hi> their Viſcount in <hi>Beſiers,</hi> and daſht out their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates teeth, (having taken Sanctuary in Saint <hi>Magdalen's</hi> Church) were in the number of thoſe whoſe ſucceſſours we glory to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. If ſo, what may we thinke of the Divine Providence which forty two yeares after gave theſe bloud-thirſty men into the hands of the <hi>Croiſſades</hi> (as very bloud-ſuckers as themſelves) who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed them in the ſelfe ſame Church, wherein they had ſpilled the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113221:12"/> bloud of others. Vengeance purſued them into the place they had choſen for a Sanctuary, and where they had exerciſed their cruelty, there they received their puniſhment. A remarkeable circumſtance to aſſure us that the finger of God's Juſtice was there. In the Hiſtory of the <hi>Kings,</hi> the Bookes of <hi>Chronicles</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> there are ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry notable examples of God's particular indignation againſt ſome, upon whom he executed Juſtice in the ſame places where they had committed their ſeverall crimes. The like you have in <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and generally every Author abounds with ſuch examples; all which I will baulke with ſilence, that I may not paſſe over two or three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable accidents to this purpoſe, in ſuch freſh memory and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all the People here, that even at this day they ſtrike the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the moſt with aſtoniſhment, however they ſtill continue in defiance to ſuch viſible ſummons from that providence which endeavours by this meanes to awake them.</p>
            <p>The death of <hi>Hampden</hi> is one. This man whom all your <hi>Noveliſts</hi> looked upon as one of the cheife Actours in the managing of their deſigne, and who was the firſt that put them in a poſture of Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Prince, received his Deaths-wound in the very ſame *<note n="*" place="margin">Chalgrove field.</note> feild where firſt he put the <hi>Militia</hi> in execution. That of the Lord <hi>Brookes</hi> is another, and perhaps you will thinke it a greater miracle. In the very moment he threatned to demoliſh the Cathedrall of <hi>Lichfield,</hi> the ſame day whereon they celebrated the memory of the <note n="*" place="margin">Saint Ghad.</note> Saint that founded it, he was ſlaine with the glance of a bullet ſent him from the hands of a dumbe perſon, and that too juſt as he was peeping out at a door; which I think hath not been hither to obſerved. Theſe circumſtances are not to paſſe our attention, being ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible teſtimonies of a Divine vengeance I might adde to the liſt of ſuch examples that horrible diſeaſe of <hi>Py<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> At the ſame time that his Conſcience was gnawed with the vermine of ambition, affecting a Tyrannicke power, God gave him for food to lice, and made him pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by ſuch a kind of death, as once he did thoſe monſtrous Tyrants, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, who both imbrued their hands in the bloud of their owne ſonnes.</p>
            <p>It remaines now, that I ſhould anſwer to ſuch objections as are drawne from the cuſtome of <hi>France,</hi> wherein you can ſpare men la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour your ſelfe with many moe beſides, that are acquainted with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113221:13"/> the preſent inconveniences which attend that way, and foreſee ſuch as may be feared for the future.</p>
            <p>In the meane time I will proceed to examine the grounds of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy. And firſt of all I ſay that Epiſcopacy is either of Divine, or at leaſt of Eccleſiaſticall Inſtitution. If of the former, then ought Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to be continued where they are, and reſtored where they are not. Put caſe it be of the latter onely, we are to examine whether it was eſtabliſh'd upon good grounds, or no; and if ſo, whether thoſe grounds be not of equall validity with us, and we obliged as much thereupon to maintaine it, I intend not at this time to diſcuſſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two queſtions: that taske hath already beene ſo amply performed by ſundry eminent writers of this age, that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines little more to be done to it. Nor will I deliver my owne opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I ſhall onely inſiſt upon two others. Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith that Epiſcopacy was inſtituted as the onely meanes to ſtoppe the current of thoſe Diviſions which ſprung at firſt among Chriſtians. <hi>Before</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that by the inſtigation of the Devill there were any fidings in Religion, and People began to ſay, I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I of</hi> Cephas, <hi>and I of</hi> Apollos, <hi>the Churches were ruled by the joint reſolutions of Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſbyters. But when every one began to fancy, that thoſe he baptized were his owne, and not Chriſt's, it was ordained throughout the whole world, that there ſhould be one choſen out of the reſt with whom the cure of the Church was to be entruſted for the rooting up of Schiſmes, and taking away all matter of diſſention.</hi> What this great Doctor ſpake ſo punctually of the Baptiſme of <hi>Paul,</hi> of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Apollo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> is nothing (in my judgement) but an alluſion to what we reade in one of the Epiſtles to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and ought to be conſtrued of all thoſe ſeeds of diviſion, which the Devill ſcattered among Chriſtians in the infancy of the Church, and ſuch as he hath throwne amongſt them ever ſince. Thus we ſee ſo many monſtrous Hereſies have beene ſtrangled by meanes of this Order; ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>oone as they ſaw the light others, after they had in a ſort empoiſoned the whole Earth. And if ſtill there have continued ſome in the World, or any ſlips of the old roote have beene remaining, it hath generally happened in ſuch places where Epiſcopacy had not it's full force, and where Councells have not enjoyed their due liberty, as in ſome of the Southerne and Eaſterne Countries, and ſome alſo of the North, where Chriſtian Religion hath ſuffered either a totall extirpation,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113221:13"/> or at leaſt ſome notable alteration by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then Epiſcopacy hath produced fruits anſwerable to their hopes who did firſt inſtitute it (as beyond all contradiction it hath) to what courſe ſhall we betake our ſelves in theſe diſtractive times, wherein the Devill is ſo buſy at his old game, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omenting Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among all thoſe whom the Spirit of God hath freed from the yoke and ſlavery of <hi>Rome?</hi> now eſpecially when there are ſo many viſible Factions amongſt us, ſome ſiding with <hi>Luther,</hi> others with <hi>Calvin,</hi> and moſt of the reſt following no other guides, then their owne apiſh unruly Fancies? what courſe I ſay ſhall we now fly to for remedy, but the example of all antiquity, in tracing their Steps, and conforming to their rules, withall applying our ſelves to thoſe Antidotes wherewith they healed the like diſtempers we ſuffer, and are upon the point to periſh under? In thoſe times the unity of the Head begat an Unity of Miſſion, this an Unity of Doctrine, and both together an Unity of all the Faithfull among themſelves. But in theſe dayes of ours, from the multitude of Paſtours equall in authority, there flowes a diverſity of Miſſion, from this a repugnancy of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and from both jointly the Schiſmes and ſidings of People; which could never have befallen us, had men contented themſelves with a meere Reformation of Epiſcopacy, and not utterly aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; Or if during their Diviſion, they had eſtabliſhed it in ſuch places as they had made themſelves Maſters of, or where they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed a Toleration. This is cleare from the example of <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Diſciples are never at oddes with themſelves, but ſtill keepe the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy cloſe and well compacted in all it's Members, through the skill of their Conductours, who have the ſole power of deciding controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies amongſt them, and they neither have authority, nor any the leaſt badge thereof, but what they derive from their Heads. So that it is a rare thing to behold any Innovation of Religion with them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Doctrine or Diſcipline, and if any ſhould ariſe, that Order doth ſo hedge it in, that it cannot proceed a ſteppe further, then they pleaſe themſelves.</p>
            <p>If examples borrowed from our Enemies be odious, let us inſiſt onely upon that of <hi>England.</hi> So long as the Biſhops were not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted in their Function<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Kingdome was not diſquieted with any Schiſmes or diſorders in the Church. There durſt not a Sectarie ſhew his head, till thoſe Chriſtian Guides were overborne with violence,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113221:14"/> and all ſuperiority among Paſtours decryed. Now if their conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture be ſound; who ſay that Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> builds not a bare alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the words of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> but a cleare obſervation, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Apoſtles times there aroſe certaine jarres among their Diſciples, ſome pretending to a right of greater preheminence by reaſon of ſome better endowments (which every one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular aſcribed to him who had baptiſed and inſtructed him) and that upon this foundation the Devill attempted to build a multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of bodies, and prevailed ſo farre, that he ſeemed to have got a ſhare in the Church then in her Infancy; have not we reaſon every moment to feare the like now from ſo many upſtart Doctrines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion, and ſo many different ſects in <hi>Europe,</hi> reſulting from that variety of Opinion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which is every where to be ſeene amongſt out Teachers? The malady is ſo great, that it ſeemes to be arrived at its height, and ſo little care is taken of applying a remedy, as if men had a deſigne palpably to betray the cauſe of God. The greateſt miſcheife I finde herein is, that ſo long as our exteriour government ſhall continue in the ſame poſture it is at this preſent, it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to heale the diſtemper, and if we go about to alter the Order eſtabliſhed, it muſt needes be from better to worſe, in as much as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſect will be buſy in tempting others after it, and ſo make a rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Body, and teare the Church in peeces.</p>
            <p>Let us once more reflect a little upon Antiquity. Had there beene ought amiſſe in the firſt inſtitution of Epiſcopacy, and had not indeed the ſpirit of God beene the ſole contriver of it for the common benefit of the Church, could his providence have given way to that generall unanimous approbation it received from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in every corner of the Univerſe? We ſee clearely, that of all the new Lawes and ſeverall alterations deviſed by the wiſedome and prudence of man, there is not any one but hath beene oppoſed in ſome part of the world, or other. Witneſſe what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>uded upon the Church either againſt the cuſtome of Antiquity or the rules of Scripture, ſuch as ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Supreme authority of one Perſon in caſes ſpirituall, the ſeverall te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s about the Enchariſt, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints, worſhiping of Images,</hi> with many other. But this decree which enables one of thoſe that are imployed in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion of the Heavenly treaſures with a power above his fellow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hath continued inviolable among all the Nations of the earth for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113221:14"/> well nigh the ſpace of fourteene hundred yeares together, not a man in all this time opening his mouth againſt it, (what ever differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of opinions, Schiſmes and Hereſies the Spirit of blindeneſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced within the pale of Chriſtianity) till this age of our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, who perſwaded themſelves they could by humane prudence ſetle among the Miniſters of the Goſpell an equality of merit, of zeale, of charity and affection, by ordaining an equality of Power and Authority, and were further confident by this meanes to cut the throate of that Tyranny, under which our Fathers for ſo long a time had groaned, as alſo to re-invite into the world that ſweetneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffability, wherewith the founders of the Church ſo expreſſely charged it ſhould be governed. And laſtly they preſumed, that if the Prelates were once outed, integrity, innocence, and good manners would be reſtored to their place in the Church againe, nor ſhould luxury, incontinence, or any other kinde of leudneſſe uſurpe their Roomes any more for ever.</p>
            <p>Theſe indeed were good wiſhes and deſires, but the meanes of perſuing them ſtarke naught. Neither did they meet with a generall likeing, divers having rejected them as fighting with that ſucceſſe which others had promiſed themſelves in the uſe of them. Did not <hi>Germany,</hi> which firſt threw the Pope out of the Saddle, and where the purity of the Goſpell was firſt reſtored to its ancient Liberty, retaine ſtill in her Churches that ſuperiority, againſt which they declaime here? 'Tis inviolably maintained in moſt countries of the North. Did the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> abjure or condemne it, <note place="margin">Cyrill.</note> when he reformed himſelfe after the example of the Proteſtants in the Weſt? Or dare any of us deny him our Communion, becauſe he retained it? Nay was he ever ſo much as adviſed to forgoe it? The luſtre and majeſty of the title he bare was no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to him from being both a confeſſour and a martyr of the ſame Chriſt we worſhip.</p>
            <p>But let us herein conſult with our moſt eminent Reformers. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> a moſt violent oppoſer of the Authors of ruine and corruption in the Church, after he hath ſpent himſelfe in heaping reproaches upon the Biſhops, calling them <hi>Idolls, and dumb Statues, idle puppets, deceitfull maskes, trunkes without branches or rootes, empty ſhadowes, ſtage-players, ſuch as were ſo farre from knowing the honour of their Function, and how to diſcharge it aright, that they did not underſtand
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113221:15"/> the Etymology of the name they bare; wolfes; breifly: tray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, murtherers, the monſters of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, the burden of the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Apoſtles of Antichriſt, moulded and fitted for the deſtruction of the world and extinguiſhing the light of the Goſpell,</hi> at laſt he comes to himſelfe againe; and tells <hi>us that he inveighs onely againſt the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of their liver, and their palpable Ignorance, as for the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he harboured not a thought againſt the Order and frame of the Church, and that nothing he had ſpoken of thoſe idle drouſie Animalls and filthy belly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gods ought to be applyed to the honeſt Paſtours, and reall Biſhops,</hi> whom he there calls <hi>the Head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Over-ſeers of the Chriſtian Church.</hi> In other places, as namely in <hi>his Captivity of Babylon,</hi> he overthrowes the ſacrament of Order, and rejecteth (as a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe fancy) their indelible character. But he quarrells not there with Biſhops alone, but even with <hi>Preiſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> avouching all <hi>the faithfull equally to be Preiſts and Deacons,</hi> and endowed with equall Authority. Notwithſtanding recollecting himſelfe, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes for <hi>the exellency of Epiſcopacy, acknowledging the name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be ſacred and ancient: and that if he deny it thoſe againſt whom he declaimes, 'tis becauſe he thinks it unlawfull to beſtow it on ſuch, whoſe corruption and filthineſſe vendors them ſo unworthy of it.</hi> In the Tract he compiled <hi>for the inſtruction of Miniſters,</hi> he cloſeth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation with an eſtabliſhment of Biſhops, to which he would have the Cities of Bohemia conforme themſelves in electing one or two, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling them with Authority over the reſt, to goe in viſitation about the Churches after the example of Saint</hi> Peter <hi>in the Acts,</hi> which he ſtileth <hi>a lawfull and Evangelicall Archiepiſcopacy.</hi> But if men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſo vainely timerous that they dare not adventure upon the reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an <hi>Apoſtolicall Inſtitution,</hi> he permits them to retaine the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of <hi>Rome, in having Biſhops to call, ordaine, and confirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a they ſhall finde capable according to the platforme and Doctrine of</hi> Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> So likewiſe you may ſee divers examples of that age, which teſtify that the opinions of thoſe times were much different from ours about the point in Queſtion. We finde in one of <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> Epiſtles to <hi>Beza,</hi> that a certaine Biſhop of <hi>Troy</hi> making a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of continuing in that profeſſion after his converſion to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, was unanimouſly received and acknowledged of all for a lawfull Prelate, whoſe Authority together with his Piety prov'd a maine advancement of the Churches good. This worthy Author
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113221:15"/> not condemning Epiſcopacy in generall, paſſeth only this verdict upon it, that in as much as none are raiſed to that dignity but by the favour of Princes, Chriſtians can have but faint hopes of reaping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great benefit thereby. In the ſame place he concludes <hi>for the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of their viſitations, as a preſent remedy to curethe naturall infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of man, who is ever declining from bad to worſe, and be ſpeakes there of Primates and Arch-biſhops,</hi> as of thoſe, who for Sanctity of life and Purity of Doctrine were deſigned to this Function in the ſeverall Cities and Sees of greateſt note: withall condemning thoſe who intrude at their owne pleaſures into the Miniſtery, &amp; conclude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is not without ſome emphaticall ground, <hi>that in the Epiſtles to</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Titus <hi>the ſeverall conditions and qualifications of Biſhops, Preiſts, and Deacons are ſo punctually deſcribed.</hi> Where it is worth your obſervation, that he marſhalls all three in their proper ranks, a pregnant evidence that he made more then two degrees of Eccleſiaſticall Order. And ſo likewiſe doth the Author of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed diſcipline in <hi>France,</hi> who in the firſt Article acquaints us with three ſorts of <hi>Miniſters, Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Paſtours, Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> quoting to this purpoſe the ſame Epiſtles with <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi> Where two things deſerve our notice, firſt the name of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and next that of <hi>Presbyters.</hi> As for the former I cannot but wonder why he ſhould confound it with that of <hi>Paſtours,</hi> &amp; then after diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh both from <hi>Preſbyters,</hi> if it be true (as many would have it) that <hi>Presbyters, Paſtours,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> were but one and the ſelfe ſame thing in the Primitive Church. As for the name of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> it is miſapplyed with us to ſuch whoſe Function ſpeakes them to be no more then <hi>Deacons.</hi> A thing utterly repugnant to the practice all ages. Whence it appeares, that he was ſomewhat aſhamed to baulke an Order which he knew the Primitive and purer Chriſtians held in ſuch ſingular eſtimation, and the Church, maugre the ſeverall corruptions in it, hath ever ſince maintained. At leaſt we may ſhrewdly ſuſpect, that he afforded this name a place there, as the print or ſhadow (at leaſt) of a Function which had beene before, and the ſeed or baſis of that which ought to have beene eſtabliſhed among the Churches in his time; then eſpecially when it might be done with the leaſt prejudice to manners or doctrine, both which it was conſtantly beleeved were moſt of all undermined by <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> The truth is, all the Divines of greateſt note with us have beene
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113221:16"/> driven upon this concluſion, whenſoever they have fallen upon the ſame Queſtion. They all joyntly condemned with extreameſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour the corruptions, which in their times were (in a ſort) the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall companions of that Profeſſion, but they never deny it its due reverence, conſidered abſtractively in it ſelfe. <hi>Calvin</hi> after he himſelfe had executed the Office of a Biſhop in <hi>Geneva,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit l. 4. c. 4.</hi> § 4.</note> diſcourſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ancient inſtitution of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in Cities, of <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> above them in Provinces, and in fine of <hi>Patriarchs</hi> advanced at the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> above both the former, ſaith, <hi>that this was done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> order to the diſcipline of the Church, and</hi> withall acknowledgeth, <hi>that Antiquity notwithſtanding ſuch innovations, had not the leaſt thought of obtruding upon the Church any other forme of government, then what God himſelfe had preſcribed in his word. That howſoever they beſtowed on that forme of their owne the name of Hierarchy, a word not extant in Scripture, yet we are not to dwell upon the notion, but to weigh the nature of the thing it ſelfe.</hi> By which paſſage, Sir, you may eaſily inferre, how this worthy Author ſtood affected to the Order we ſpeake of. That of <hi>Beza</hi> an able judicious writer (if we reflect upon the times he liv'd in) is no leſſe for our purpoſe, then the former. He grants in one place, that <hi>Epiſcopacy was uſefull in the Church,</hi> and that <hi>the diſtinction of Biſhops and Arch-biſhops was firſt inſtituted for the read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Synods, and managing the affaires of the Church with more ſteadineſſe.</hi> To wave what this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Auth or hath farther delivered upon the Queſtion, who will not hence conclude (if he caſt but an eye upon the many difficulties they meet with that are to ſteere the inclinations of men either in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Policy) that he was ſo farre from diſallowing <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that on the contrary he approv'd it as an Inſtitution of higheſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to Chriſtianity? And in the particular caſe of <hi>England,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body knowes, that theſe two eminent Perſons abſolutely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ibed to its continuance there. The one of which hath publiſhed ſo much to the world in a Tract againſt <hi>Saravia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and doth not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo ſpeake expreſſely in behalfe of thoſe in that Kingdome, which the men of this generation would quite extirpate?</p>
            <p>But let us farther examine their opinion who ſpeake of the thing in generall, <hi>Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emptory, that <hi>to make up thoſe breathes in the Church which happened after the Apoſtles times, there was one ſet ever the reſt of the Presbyters, and call'd by way of eminence Biſhop,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113221:16"/> whereto he ſubjoyneth, <hi>that in relation to that primitive order and diſcipline of the Church, there hath ever beene one ranked before the reſt of his Brethren to keepe them within compaſſe, and to prevent the broaching of any new doctrines. Melanchton</hi> is yet more expreſſe. <hi>The policy of the Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is the exteriour face thereof, is compounded of two ingredients. The firſt is the Miniſtery, a thing of Gods owne immediate inſtitution, (and it containes five parts, 1. The right of calling and ordaining Miniſters. 2. The injunction to preach the Goſpell. 3. The power of remitting ſinnes. 4. of adminiſtring the Sacraments, and 5. The right of exerciſing Juriſdiction upon Offenders by excommunication.) The ſecond is the humane Conſtitutions of Biſhops, and Councells, who are to regulate the degrees of Miniſters, and the difference of time and place when and where to execute their Functions. Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thoſe conſtitutions are to be maintained for the cheriſhing of good Order, yet ſo as they be drained from all tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of ſuperſtition,</hi> And he gives the reaſon, <hi>becauſe they have a kinde of right naturall, the very law of nature obligeing us to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant obſervation of good order in the conduct of our lives.</hi> A paſſage very part for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as noting unto us the impoſſibility of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing any Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſorders without it. For the Members will then teare one another in peices, and the body which kept them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſo cloſe and ſtrict an union, <hi>cannot long mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taine the peace and harmony which that order as the ſoule infuſed into them,</hi> as Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> ſomewhere ſpeaketh. I cannot wave neither a paſſage I have ſometimes read in <hi>Hierome Savanarola,</hi> a bitter enemy to the corruption of the Clergy, and one that vehemently declaim'd againſt the diſorders of the Church. <hi>If</hi> (faith he in his booke <hi>de veritate Fidei) there ſhall happen any kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty difficult ſcruple in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the faithfull, the Biſhops are they that muſt decide the Queſtion:</hi> which muſt needes be conſtrued of that ſuperiority, whereby they are to bridle the boldneſſe and inſolence of ſuch as being hurried on with a ſpirit of confuſion, diſquiet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Church with maladies hard to be cured. This mov'd the other <hi>Hierome</hi> about 1200 yeares agoe to avouch, that the <hi>prosperity of the Church did ſo mainely depend upon the ſuperiour Miniſter, that were it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, there would be as many Schiſmes among Chriſtians, as Presbyters. Which conſequent</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Arch-biſhop of Spalata) is manifeſtly ſeene in ſuch of the reformed Churches as have abandoned Epiſcopacy.</hi> This
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113221:17"/> was the reaſon why the Princes and all thoſe of the Clergy that ſubſcribed to the <hi>Ausburge Confeſſion,</hi> did joine in ſuch an open Proteſtation before God and Man, that they ſought not for the extirpation of it. They were as well acquainted as we with the corruption of the Biſhops, and had as much (at leaſt) to feare from their continuance, as we can poſſibly have. And yet to prevent the unavoidable neceſſity of that confuſion, into which they would otherwiſe have fallen, they unanimouſly agreed upon the defence of that Ancient Order, and to oppoſe with all eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſuch as ſhould endeavour the abolition of the ſame. This they hotly purſued, not barely in order to Religion which they laboured to reſcue from Romiſh ſlavery, but alſo for ſome ſecular conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, intwiſted with Religion it ſelfe; as the union and concord of the People, without which it would be a very hard taske for them to preſerve their ſeverall Rights and Prerogatives entire. This alſo is the reaſon why the ſucceeding Emperours made ſo many attempts to bereave the German Proteſtants of this Order, being taught by experience that Epiſcopacy keepes them cloſer together, and that this union of the People is the greateſt obſtacle to their ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. Had there been any Biſhops in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> all the reſt of the reformed parts in <hi>Germany</hi> would have ſtrucke in for their defence, and engaged themſelves in the ſame quarrell, <hi>France</hi> it ſelfe would not have ſuffered them to be made ſuch an eaſy prey to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> But all things ſeemed to conſpire the ruine of that State, which to the prejudice of it's owne particular intereſts, the intereſts of Chriſtendome, and of all thoſe of the North (who had declared themſelves both againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> and againſt all ſuch as aim'd at an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Monarchy) would needs ſet on foot new maximes, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the project of a reformation, from which it had ſo many viſible evills to feare.</p>
            <p>I have long ſince exceeded the bounds of a Letter, and (contrary to my firſt thoughts) have well-nigh ſwelled it into a Volume. The feare I have to treſpaſſe upon your patience makes me paſſe by a whole cloud of our firſt Reformers, all jointly ſubſcribing to the ſame concluſion. And beſides, the ſmall remnant of time behind will not ſuffer me to recall into your memory what thoſe of our Age deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine upon the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>I have ſcarce heard of any able and judicious Divine with us, who values not this Ancient Order as the band and inſtrument of that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113221:17"/> peice which Chriſt preached. I know very well that all your <hi>nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and popular Judgements doe leane another way, and that the number of theſe exceeds by much that of the more knowing ſort. Nor am I ignorant, that there be ſome able malicious heads amongſt us, which clearely ſee the truth, but cannot affect it; they are ſo tranſported with the love of an unlawfull and counterfeite liberty, that they never buſy themſelves about the prevention of that diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which it will inevitably (ſooner or later) pull upon them and all ſuch as adhere to them.</p>
            <p>Mounſieur <hi>du Mouli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is none of that number. This gallant man (whom God honoured with ſo many eminent gifts above all that were either the Authors or Abettours of ſuch corruptions as had crept into the Church) is peremptory in the point (appealing to the generall ſuffrage of Eccleſiaſticall ſtory) that <hi>immediately after the times of the Apoſtles, or indeed while they were yet living, there begun in every City to be one of the Paſtours ſet over the reſt, diſtinguiſhed by the Title of Biſhop, and inveſted with a power above his fellowes, to prevent that confuſion which ordinarily flowes from equality, &amp; this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution met with a generall approbation; whence</hi> (ſaith He) <hi>we cannot excuſe</hi> Aërius <hi>for oppoſing the determination of the Church in his time, when the difference ſtood onely in point of Diſcipline.</hi> A little after he concludes, that <hi>in</hi> England <hi>God made uſe of certaine Biſhops out of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>for accompliſhing that glorious worke of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; whereupon the name and dignity Epiſcopall hath beene derived ſucceſſively unto ſuch his Miniſters, whom he hath raiſed up to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the errours and corruption of men. That in other places where God made choice of Presbyters and Doctours, the Paſtours of the Church are barely ſtiled Miniſters, the People with us being not able to digeſt the names of Preiſts and Biſhops, the bad converſation of ſuch as went under that name having rendred them ſo extreamely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dious.</hi> Which yet is but a ſlender ground for their extirpation, as I ſhall cleare anon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonius de Dominis,</hi> an able m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n without queſtion, and a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed adverſary to the Romiſh Tyranny (under which in fine he pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed) maintaines with great force of reaſon, that <hi>the Election of Miniſters, to wit, of Biſhops and Preiſts, was made by the Apoſtles ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inſtitution of Chriſt; that the Church hath alwaies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and profeſſed a difference betwixt them; the diverſity of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113221:18"/> their functions and the generall practice of antiquity having ever ranked Biſhops before Preſbyters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the ſame place he takes the paints to collect and ſalve the ſeverall paſſages of Scripture which ſeemingly ſpeake the contrary, as alſo thoſe in the Fathers, and Canons of Councels. Whereupon he gives us a very remarkeable obſervation (which I gave you a light touch of before) and 'tis this, That <hi>all ſuch as forſooke the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Catholicke Church (as the Novatians and Donatiſts) would yet ſtill retaine their Biſhops, knowing very well that the Church could not poſſibly ſubſiſt without them, as being abſolutely neceſſary in the Catholique Church, of which every one in particular would pretend to be a Member.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hence is it that in <hi>Rome</hi> there have ſometimes beene three at once; one of the <hi>Catholiques,</hi> who was the lawfull and true one; the other two, of thoſe two bodies (or rather diſmembred peeces of the Church) which they ſet up for no other reaſon, but becauſe they would otherwiſe have beene convicted to be without the pale of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I hope Monſieur <hi>Blondell</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> when they have once purged Epiſcopacy from ſuch corruptions as the ſpirit of lying had faſtened upon it (on purpoſe to render it as pernicious in the uſe, is it was ſacred in the inſtitution) will no longer keepe alooſe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> opinions from us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut ſadly laying to heart the evills which will ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably oppreſſe the whole Church, if once it be deprived of it's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient forme of government, they will contribute ſuch advice to this miſerable Country, as their knowledge and honeſty ſhall ſuggeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: nor continue to ſtifle a knowne truth, as many at this day (ſtrangers to neither of us) ſo unconſcionably doe. Let the <hi>Monkes</hi> grumble (as long as they pleaſe) againſt that Order, to which they cannot endure their owne extravagant rules ſhould be any way ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate. Let the inſolent and ſaucy <hi>Jeſuite</hi> oppoſe their authority, and ſlinke out of their ſight for feare they ſhould take notice of his Corruption. But let us whoſe thoughts ought to be moſt pure, and actions moſt regular, ſubmit unto thoſe maximes to which theſe fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen laſt Centuries have paid an univerſall obedience. Who knowes not that if the Power delegated to the Miniſters of the Goſpell ſhould be equally ſhared amongſt all, Confuſion and Diviſion muſt needs be the iſſue? Had not the <hi>Jewes</hi> (who were but an inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113221:18"/> Body in reſpect of us Chriſtians) their <hi>High Preiſt,</hi> anſwerable to our Biſhop in every particular Church? who marched before the reſt, enjoyed divers peculiar prerogatives above his Brethren, and had certaine diſtinct functions in point of Religion apperteining to him. Doth not even reaſon informe us, that 'tis impoſſible for any Congregation or Society of men to keepe long together, if there be not ſome one ſet over the reſt, that (like an indiſſoluble chaine) is to reſtraine the ſeverall members (how different and diſagreeing ſoever among themſelves) within the limits of their proper cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. What would be the iſſue of all our Aſſemblyes, had they not a preſident over them? by meanes whereof we ſtill retaine an <hi>Idea</hi> of that Churches practiſe, which we have abandoned for it's impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. And this indeed is the onely Antidote for all ſores and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in the Church; no remedy ſo preſent and Soveraigne; it being impoſſible for the ſame man to differ from himſelfe. We ſee that Families are ever at unity when they beare an orderly ſubjection to the Maſter of the Houſe, be there never ſo many private jarrings of opinions among the ſeverall members.</p>
            <p>Examine we the matter yet a little further. Is there any thing more agreeable to reaſon, then that the leſſe depend upon the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the weake and feeble upon the ſtrong? in a word, to behold that ſubordination in the world, that where any prejudiciall counſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or reſolutions ſhall happen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e propoſed, they may be timouſly check'd by ſome intervening authority, and kept within the bounds preſcribed them.</p>
            <p>How many may we every day ſee attempting to paſſe the bounds of their abilities and profeſſions? and of what a banefull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the impunity of ſuch irregularities may prove, I leave it for any man to determine. This I'me ſure made the Divine Providence ſpeake by the mouth of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 29.</note> 
               <hi>when the Prophets ſpeake, there ſhould be ſome to judge.</hi> That which followes is very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable; <note n="*" place="margin">v 33.</note> 
               <hi>The spirits of the Prophets are ſubject unto the Prophets;</hi> whereof preſently he renders the reaſon, For <note n="*" place="margin">v. 34.</note> 
               <hi>God is not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Confuſion, but of Peace, as in all Churches of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold, Sir, at a nearer diſtance the reaſons for which this Order was firſt eſtabliſhed, which in my judgement are of equall force for the continuance of it to all ages; ſeeing you have as great cauſe now as ever to feare thoſe inconveniences which attend on equality.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113221:19"/> You have Councels to be aſſembled, Schiſmes to be compoſed. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques to be convinced, and many ill appointed Churches to be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited.</p>
            <p>But there is yet a more ſpeciall and preſſing motive in the caſe of <hi>England,</hi> to wit, the Genius of the People, who being accuſtomed to gaze upon a gorgeous outſide, will not without much reluctancy be drawne to yeild any manner of reverence and ſubmiſſion to ſuch as ſtand not upon the vantage-ground of honour. Witneſſe their Divines and all the <hi>gowned tribe.</hi> Let their vertues be never ſo legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Great ones looke upon them but as ſo many <hi>ſilly fellowes in blacke,</hi> extracted out of the ſcumme of the People, who for their part thinke they doe them a great honour, if they ſhall vouchſafe to uſe them as their companions. The caſe being thus, what may we thinke would attend the extirpation of Epiſcopacy out of that Kingdome, but the utter contempt of Chriſtianity?</p>
            <p>From vilifying the perſons, 'tis ordinary to proceed next to a ſlighting of the Profeſſion, though never ſo ſacred. And if they put ſuch a cheape eſteeme upon the Perſons of thoſe that are to direct the Conſcience, and watch over the ſoule, with what oſcitancy and indevotion will all their counſels and inſtructions be entertained amongſt them? 'Tis indeed the dignity of the Prelates which hath hitherto ſupported the dignity of Religion, and if any manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect hath beene paid them, it was firſt excited by the Majeſty and luſtre of that ſuperiority wherewith God hath inveſted them, as the moſt naturall meanes to keepe in an Evangelicall awe a People, whoſe very Genius ſeconded with exceſſe of riches and ſecurity, hath merited them the name of <hi>the moſt inſolent People in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But they tell us, that the Biſhops of meere Overſeers were become abſolute Lords; and of Rulers had transformed themſelves into Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants: which indeed may be true of ſome, but not of all. How many have there beene in <hi>England</hi> ſince the Reformation ſo farre from the leaſt ſmacke of their Predeceſſours or any of their fellow brethrens vanity, that on the contrary in examples of modeſty and and humility they have left moſt of the truly Reformed Paſtours in <hi>Europe</hi> behind them? who knowes not that the now Biſhop of <hi>Dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> notwithſtanding the large revenues he formerly enjoyed, and the ſeverall titles of honour particularly annexed to that Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113221:19"/> hath manifeſted to the world that he is caſt in the ſame mould with thoſe untainted ſoules of the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>All men may reade his temper, and what ſpirit ſwayed him in his greateſt proſperity, inaſmuch as now ſharing in the common calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, depriv'd of all his livelyhood, and brought to indigence, thrown downe from ſo high a pitch of greatneſſe to ſo low an ebbe, from ſo much honour to ſo much infamy, ſhut up, as it were in a priſon, without eaſe, without liberty, and almoſt without a freind too, aged about foureſcore and five or ſix yeares; he beares it all out with ſuch compoſedneſſe of ſpirit, ſuch an abſolute reſignation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Divine Providence in the midſt of theſe his trialls, that he ſeemes to have no part in the corruption of the Times, and thoſe impurities wherewith they charge his Brethren: ſuch a large por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he hath in the innocence and vertues of the Primitive Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
            <p>Did ever any man behold a more Apoſtolique man, then the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <note n="*" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>vſher.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Primate of Ireland?</hi> I applaud not now the learning either of the one, or other. I ſpeake onely of their piety, that characteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall vertue of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Could any the moſt active and noted adverſaries of Epiſcopacy ever blemiſh the converſation of Doctor <hi>Bromhall</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> of <hi>Jewell, Bilſon, Hall, Downham, Davenant, Sands, Abbot, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Prideaux,</hi> and a large Catalogue beſides of ſuch whoſe vertues are not yet come to my knowledge, no more then their names? For all thoſe prerogatives they enjoy above other men by reaſon of the Character they beare, for all that ſuperiority and thoſe titles full of pompe and magnificence the Lawes of the Land have allowed them; did ever any know them give the leaſt ſcandall to the moſt ſcrupulous conſcience, or the leaſt occaſion for the meaneſt Subject to complaine of them? On the contrary, the whole courſe of their lives is a copy worthy the imitation not onely of ſuch as had need to reforme themſelves, but even of the moſt unblameable perſons. I ſhould but wrong their modeſties in proceeding any further. And I would be loath to diſtaſt them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other intent then ſimply to deſcribe them. However I ſhall confidently a vouch thus much, that they live in Epiſcopacy with much more integrity, then any of their Perſecutours do in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; as being conformable to their intention who firſt gave life
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113221:20"/> unto it. The Divine Authours of ſo ſacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Ordinance knew well enough what high conceits are apt to ſurprize the ſoules of men when once they are lifted up above others: and hence was it that of ſo many names wherewith the Apoſtles inveſted the Rulers of the Church, they pitch't upon the name of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for ſuch as were to fit at the Sterne. There were others that carried more ſtate and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre with them, as that of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſtour,</hi> wherewith <hi>homer</hi> honours his King, of <hi>Elder,</hi> of <hi>Doctour,</hi> of <hi>Preſident,</hi> of <hi>Cheife.</hi> But this is a name of toile and diligence, by which the firſt impoſers of it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to containe ſuch as they had exalted above the ranke of others within the bounds of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling. And agreeable hereunto, what paines have the men we named ever denied to conſecrate unto the Church? Have they ever thwarted the Rules of their firſt Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And if the name they beare ſpeakes them engaged to a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall taske in managing of publicke affaires, have they not ever ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied all the powers of their ſoules to the purſuance of the ſame? Yes, they have done it with a flaming and ſaint-like zeale, and have made the world read in their Actions their conſtant readineſſe to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their lives and fortunes to the good of their Brethren.</p>
            <p>But they are traduced for countenancing Popery where it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and ſcattering ſome new ſeeds thereof where it had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate.</p>
            <p>This may be true of ſome, but is a groſſe ſlander upon the moſt of them.</p>
            <p>If it had a ſimple toleration, this was done moſtly out of a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table regard towards the Reformed Churches in Popiſh Dominio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; nay further for the good of the Papiſts themſelves whom they ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated. Their examples, their converſation, their affable deportment might happily one day draw them over to a Profeſſion from which baniſhments and other the like rigorous courſes doe commonly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them. Religion cannot be forced upon the ſoule. God muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Infuſe it himſelfe, or perſwade it by men. Had the Biſhops leaned never ſo little to the Popiſh Party, and could they have been induced by any warping in opinion to favour thoſe of that Religion when the Proteſtants were overborne in <hi>Ireland,</hi> they would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly have uſed them with more humanity when they had them at their mercy; as an argument of that good correſpondence betwixt them.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113221:20"/>
            <p>But the caſe was much otherwiſe, ſo as never were any in a more deplorable condition, then they. There is no manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, diſgrace, loſſe &amp; perſecution, which hath not befallen them. Had the Biſhops there beene ſuch as the common voice proclaimes them, would they not have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpared? And if they had not been Proteſtants indeed, would they not have gone over to the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, and have followed the prevailing party? was there for all this, I will not ſay a Biſhop, but even any well affected to Epiſcopacy, whom the threats of Fire and Sword could prevaile with to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Popery, and renounce the Reformed Religion?</p>
            <p>They further tell us, that they doated too much upon titles of pride and ambition, and ſuch honours as the ſuperſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of blinder times beſtowed on them. Beſhrew their hearts that did ſo. But the Innocent have reaſon to complaine of hard dealing, if they muſt be liſted with the guilty, were there indeed any ſuch at all. You will pardon me if I ſhall hereupon avouch, that many even of our owne men have ſometimes picked a quarrell where there needed none. I remember we once fell in diſcourſe upon this argument, and how after ſome ſlight debate you agreed with me in the upſhot, that the Overſeers of the Church ought in all reaſon to be inveſted with ſome diſtinct and peculiar character to draw reſpect from inferiours; That this was ever the practice of the Church, and the very intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that eſtabliſhed a ſuperiority therein. Whence aroſe the ſeverall appellations of <hi>Father, Paternity, Pope, Holineſſe,</hi> with many ſuch in uſe with antiquity. Nor is <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> and the <hi>respects</hi> due unto it commended unto us with more earneſtneſſe, then former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were. As God ſeemes to have graven his image in a more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent manner upon the face of ſuch as are in authority, thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting his unity, (an unity not to be parallell'd with any thing in the world) in like ſort hath the Church univerſall honoured them with ſuch prerogatives as might beſt denote the obedience due to God himſelfe who conferred that function upon them. Hence doth the Author of that Epiſtle to the <hi>Trallians,</hi> which goes under the name of Saint <hi>Ignatius,</hi> uſe theſe expreſſe tearmes; <hi>Reverence your Biſhop as yee doe Chriſt, reſerving alſo a ſhare in the honour to the Presbyters, that ſo by your ſubjection to the Biſhop and the Presbytery, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be ſanctified in all things.</hi> This Presbytery, as he there interprets it himſelfe, is the <hi>Colledge of Presbyters, a ſacred Aſſembly, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoaps
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113221:21"/> Councellors, and ſuch as we call Aſſeſſours in civill Courts,</hi> to whom he enjoynes obedience <hi>as to the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Where the diſtinction he makes betwixt the honour due to Biſhops and that appertaining to Presbyters is worth our obſervation. For he ſaith that the former are to be reverenc'd as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the other as his Apoſtles; which he would never have done had he not preſumed that they, who were intruſted with the care of the Church, did go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne it according to the rules of their Maſter, ſurrendring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the obedience of his holy ſpirit, and theſe holding faſt to their head, won authority to their Miniſtery and all their inſtructions by that conformity betwixt them.</p>
            <p>I am not Ignorant that ſome cavill at this exhortation, and take occaſion hereby to condemne that age of having firſt attempted upon the honour and reſpect due unto Chriſt; as if by ſuch expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions the Biſhops were put into the ballance with him; but theſe men conſider not how all this was grounded upon Scripture; <hi>He that heareth you heareth me; They have not rejected you but mee; Obey th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that have the rule over you.</hi> And beſides, what <hi>Ignatius</hi> enjoines in behalfe of <hi>Biſhops, Polycarpus</hi> a diſciple of the Apoſtles expreſſely recommendeth in behalfe of <hi>Preiſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> in that excellent Epiſtle he wrote to the <hi>Philippians;</hi> which we have only ſeene in manuſcript. <hi>Abſtaining</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from theſe things, be ye ſubject to the Preiſts and to the Deacons, as unto God and Chriſt:</hi> the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion was uſed by the Primitive Doctours of the Church in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting the People to obey their Kings and Princes, which they borrowed from an Epiſtle fathered upon <hi>Barnabas,</hi> not <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>This E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of</hi> Barnabas <hi>was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> firſt printed at</hi> Oxford <hi>by the Lord Primate of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and ſince at</hi> Paris.</note> yet publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the world. What inconvenience can there be in beſtowing that upon one which hath beene given to many, and allowing as much to a Biſhop, as hath beene granted an Aſſembly of Presbyters, ſeeing that (in the language of antiquity) <hi>the care of the Church which was diſperſed in the whole body, is united in him, and that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which had beene ſcattered amongſt ſo many, wholly devolved upon him?</hi> Suppoſe this corruption in manners they talke of were ſuch indeed, or worſe; ſuppoſe farther, that the Biſhops were guilty of ſome errours in Doctrine; may we for all this ſuppreſſe them? no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, nay we are not ſo much as to decline theirs or any man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> company upon this ground alone, if we will beleeve one of our moſt able and judicious writers; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> I meane, who in his <hi>Lecture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113221:21"/> Of the Church, hath</hi> this paſſage, <hi>that we ought not to deny a diſeaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon the benefit of our ſociety, if the malady be not mortall and contagious. That in the body the ſeparation of any one part is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, what errour ſoever hath infected it, except it be Hereſie or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, otherwiſe there can be no juſt cauſe of doing ſo.</hi> As for the depravation of manners he is yet more expreſſe, affirmeing it <hi>downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right folly for any man to conceive that a ſufficient ground of ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and</hi> alleadging the words of Chriſt, <hi>they ſit in Moſes chairs, what therefore they bid you, that doe;</hi> and he gives the reaſon, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there is purity of Doctrine, God muſt needs have a Church, though encombred with a multitude of faults.</hi> Now if this eminent writer had occaſion to ſpeake thus, what a groſſe ſhame is it for ſuch as have nothing to object againſt their Biſhops, but the bare corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of manners, to endeavour not only a ſimple ſeperation from them, but a totall ſuppreſſion of them? As for their Doctrine, that's Scot-free from cenſure; 'tis indeed ſo pure, that it agrees in every particular with that of our beſt reformed Divines, witneſſe their ſeverall Tracts of the <hi>Euchariſt, The power of the Pope, The right of Kings, The adoration of Images,</hi> and the like; which aſſure us, that thoſe which at this day advance the purity of Religion, are their deſerving ſucceſſors that laboured ſo much in the firſt eſtabliſhing of it. Such were the Prelates God employed in this great worke, the Arch-biſhops of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> &amp; <hi>Yorke,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>London, Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in <hi>Peter Martyrs</hi> time, <hi>Cran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, Ridley, Lati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, Hooper,</hi> men all famous in their generations, and ſuch as knew how to weild a Biſhoprick. Moſt of which dyed martyrs in that hot Combat they maintained againſt the Errours and impieties of their times. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them (when men durſt ſcarce mutter of a Reformation) one of the Biſhops of <hi>Lincoln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> couragiouſly entred the Liſts with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry<note place="margin">Groſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>head.</note> and Superſtition into which the Church was then plunged. And he performed the Combate with ſo much gallantry, that the common ſuffrage of all good men after him gave him this honorary title. <hi>The Hammer of Rome.</hi> Yet for all this they of <hi>London</hi> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e him and the reſt I have named you the common the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives, both in the Preſſe, and in the Pulpit. They ſpare not to call them in publique <hi>a packe of impoſtours, and Hypocrites, ſuch as never trac'd the paths of Chriſtianity but in a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling poſture, their ſoules being drunke with the cup of abdomination,</hi> what fellowſhip can
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113221:22"/> we have with ſuch a generation as this? We, who have ever paid ſo much honour and eſteeme to the memory of thoſe worthy men, that we have placed them in the ranke and calendar of our Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Nay our moſt upright and conſcientious Divines have propoſed each circumſtance of their lives and deaths, as the moſt exquiſite patternes in all <hi>Europe</hi> (and perhaps in the whole world beſides) of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied conſtancy in aſſerting Truth and ſuppreſſing falſhood.</p>
            <p>Finally, they are accuſed for intermedling too much in State affaires. They will needs have it unlawfull for them to beare any ſhare in the adminiſtration of Juſtice, and that ſuch priviledges ſhould be annexed to Epiſcopacy, which (ſay they) are incompatible with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y but the Secular Authority, and therefore they tooke care to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt them of the ſame in the beginning of this Parliament. They which harpe ſo much upon this ſtring are the very ſame malignant Spirits of which I have formerly given you the character. Had they but any ſhadow of reaſon, is it poſſible they ſhould thus fight againſt the cuſtome and example of ſo many ages both in their owne &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Countries? Who knowes not that the Conſtitutions of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt conſequence in any State have bin made in Councells &amp; Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Biſhops? What elſe meaneth that ancient Ordinance (of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 900 yeares ſtanding) which pronounceth all <hi>Elections of Kings void, where the Biſhops and cheife of the People are denyed their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> And whence aroſe the cuſtome, in all debates of preſerving inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances &amp; ſucceſſions in families of having as much recourſe to Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall as Regall Authority in that behalfe? We finde that King <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 928. by expreſſe Statute joyned the Biſhops in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with the Juſtices Secular, to ſtop the current of Injuſtice, and to root out all the ſeedes thereof. Thoſe employments did not divert them from the care of the Church Councels were no whit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, we finde that in this Age (or a little before) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the barbariſme of the <hi>Saxons</hi> had almoſt ſpent it ſelf and men begu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to taſt the ſweetneſſe of Chriſtianity, that the Biſhops (thereupon reſuming their Authority, and following the advice of one <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Mayence)</hi> ordained, that every Presbyter ſhould year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give an account of his Miniſtery to the Biſhop, who likewiſe for his part was yearly to viſit his Dioceſſe, &amp; in like manner to yeild an account of his proceedings to the Metropolitan; theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113221:22"/> Ordinances (tending all to the eſtabliſhment of purity in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) were with all rigour put in execution, notwithſtanding they ſet a part ſome time for ſecular affaires. And this is further very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable, that Biſhops themſelves made lawes for the government of the People; We finde it amongſt others in one <hi>Odon</hi> Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who exhorteth the Prince to yeeld all manner of obedience and ſubmiſſion to the Biſhops, which ſpeakes the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of their Power in this Kingdome: a power which I can ſee no cauſe ſhould be denied them, if thoſe that are inveſted with it be ſincere Profeſſors of true Chriſtianity (as they ought to be who are preferred to Biſhopricks) no more then their right of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, a right common to them with all the Biſhops that ever have beene in the world, and to which thoſe of this Kingdome have a ſtronger title, it being but the ſmall remnant of that great power they had once, and which they mannaged wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much diſcretion. Nor was it ever knowne that either King or People endeavoured their extirpation heretofore, no not ſo much as to exerciſe my ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour upon their perſons, for about eleven hundred yeares together, ſince the tyranny of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings forced them to quit the Realm and retire themſelves to <hi>France,</hi> that they might enjoy more caſe and liberty of Conſcience in the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>If ever their Votes in Parliament were lyable to ſuſpicion, it was doubtleſſe in the reigne of <hi>Henry the</hi> 8, when they had ſo ſtraight a dependance upon <hi>Rome;</hi> that Prince having in a manner ſhaken off the Romiſh yoake, and by his owne ſole authority taken upon him the government of the Church of England (which Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> had heretofore freely reſigned to <hi>Edward the Confeſſour)</hi> had juſt cauſe to feare that in thoſe Conventions they would betray his intereſts<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or of the <hi>Holy See's</hi> ſake, (as they call it) and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent that he runne a great hazard of his owne Prerogative in not excluding them. Notwithſtanding be never had ſuch a thought. No more had <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, nor Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe Princes had more to feare for the Rights of their Crowne, (which they reſcued from the Romiſh Subjection) then the People at this day can poſſibly have for their liberties and Priviledges. Their Religion then bound them to what (in all probability) was very prejudiciall to the Rights of their Kings nothing doth now oblig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them to the leaſt diſadvantage of the People.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113221:23"/>
            <p>Then they ſwore obedience to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> now they do it to none but to God himſelfe. Then the diſcipline of the Church had well-nigh ſuffered a totall ſubverſion, and <hi>England</hi> (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of <hi>Poland)</hi> might have conceived that the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity alone, without Biſhops, were intruſted with the Reformation of the Church, and that there was no more need of Prelates for Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors of State, that is, to ſit in Parliament. Notwithſtanding nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did that Example nor theſe conſiderations prove prejudiciall to the Biſhops: The Fundamentall law of the Realme, by which they are eſtabliſhed, together with the neceſſity of maintainin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them, and beſides that ſundry the moſt eminent amongſt them had couragiouſly ſacrificed their lives in behalfe of Chriſtianity, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſed all other conſiderations whatſoever. And the law which firſt ſeated them in Parliament, expects them there ſtill; now eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leaſed to make uſe of Publicke votes for the government of the Church, they are of more importance then eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. They are in <hi>England,</hi> as in our Aſſemblies of State, or as the Clergy in our higheſt Courts of Juſtice. Which of our Kings, (who are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Monarchs, without ſharing their Power, either with People or Parliaments (as they do in other places) which of them I ſay, did ever entertaine a thought of debarring the Biſhops this Priviledge. We finde indeed in a certaine old Conſtitution, that one of our Kings out of a zealous and pious intent, making (it ſeemes) a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of diverting them from the ſervice of God, diſcharged the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all, except the Abbat of Saint <hi>Denys,</hi> from aſſiſting at Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and hearing criminall caſes; but we finde not that this Ordinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was ever put in execution: but on the contrary that the weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> employments of thoſe times were wholly devolved upon <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> whoſe abilities and honeſty won them ſuch a generall repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that the cuſtome then was for Princes to ſelect, among others, two Biſhops for the cheife of their retinue, to be the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Court,</hi> and withall to ſee that juſtice were exactly and due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> adminiſtred. They had likewiſe two Maſters <hi>of Requeſts</hi> continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attending on them, one of which was alwayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Clergy-m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> who gave <hi>preſent Juſtice.</hi> And we finde in a certaine Conſtitutio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of one of our <hi>Philips,</hi> that of five appointed to give anſwer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch Petitions as were preſented in Parliaments, two were to be Lay-men, and three Clerkes.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:113221:23"/>
            <p>But what neede we go farther then <hi>England</hi> to warrant the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of this cuſtome? debarre the Biſhops their right of ſitting in Parliament, and what reſpect will a proud licentious People af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the Clergy? you may aſſure your ſelfe none at all. Let them uſe what meanes they can to make them, their Synods, or Councells, of any eſteeme with them, they will conforme no further to them then they pleaſe themſelves. Indeed to diſvote Biſhops in ſuch Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, is to bereave them of all Authority, and to open a gap for any wilde Chrochers in point of Religion to enter in that Kingdome. 'Tis in a word, to ſuppreſſe the Biſhops themſelves, to throw downe the Pillars of the Church, and ſo to render the conſervation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Purity impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Perhaps Sir, you may thinke I ſpeake in this more then comes to my ſhare, being one who profeſſe to have no portion in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo much to abhorre the Superſtition of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing ſuch things as ſome upon divers pretences, (either out of ignorance or malice) have introduced into the world, to the great prejudice and diſquiet thereof, and in derogation to the juſt liberty of Conſcience. But if you pleaſe to reflect a little upon that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious claſhing of opinions, which at this day divides <hi>England</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo many ſeverall ſects, you will certainely conclude with me, that in caſe this Order be once aboliſhed, neither innocence of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nor integrity of doctrine, can any longer enjoy a place in that Church. The reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obvious, if it be but conſidered how, ſince the diſcontinuing of Epiſcopall Power in that Kingdome, thoſe that owe obedience and ſhould be accountable for their doctrines to the Biſhops, do now live in ſuch a horrible faſhion (as I have allready inform'd you) that we may ſafely beleeve the moſt of them are the ſpawne of ſuch as were once diſgorged out of the mouth of Hell, and diſperſed in the Church to ſtifle Chriſtianity in her Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, rather then the ſucceſſors of thoſe that have beene the conſtant aſſertors of truth and oppoſers of falſhood. Witneſſe the ſeverall impieties and hereſies both ancient and moderne, where with they empoyſon the ſoules of that People, who (in the common confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) liſten to them, blindely ſwallowing downe (under pretence of Reformation) all ſorts of fancies and doctrines indifferently. The moſt abſurd dreames of the old <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> the moſt pernicious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of <hi>Origen,</hi> the moſt infamous libertiniſme of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:113221:24"/> and the moſt execrable impieties of the <hi>Soci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ians,</hi> doe uſually take up the greateſt part of their Sermons, the reſt being deſigned either for inflaming the Auditours with the coales of ſedition, and ſetting both parties at an irreconcileable diſtance; or elſe to embaſe all manners to the loweſt degree of corruption. Yet in this generall depravation, God hath reſerv'd for himſelfe ſome well diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and indued them with courage to enquire into their actions, and to brand the crimes of the Age.</p>
            <p>They have ſtoutly expreſs'd their diſlike of what hath beene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly delivered by many hundred Preachers in that Kingdome. I will not preſent you with an exact liſt of all they have publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Judge with your ſelfe, if there be any impiety thoſe men will make ſcruple of, many of whom (out of an extreame unheard of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence) have had the boldneſſe to defame in the open pulpit ſome of the other ſex, whom they could not tempt to lewdneſſe in their private Houſes. I am very credibly informed that their names were preſented to the Parliament, but could never heare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo much as intended them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this in my opinion was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> crying ſinne, then that of the <hi>Ghoſtly Father,</hi> who ſeduced a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in time of confeſſion. There is in this an unparallel'd kind of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, and ſuch as you will find farre to ſurpaſſe the greateſt crim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which have ever beene charged upon any Hereticke in the World. Such diſorders were not to be heard of till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Biſhops were outed of their Juriſdiction, and ill Church diſcipline robbed of it's force and vertue, notwithſtanding the naturall irregularity of that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Three yeares Anarchy and Independance in the Church have plunged that State into more confuſion then all the Civill Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caſe, proſperity, and long enjoyed plenty, the wildneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchedneſſe of many of their Princes in former times could do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. There be ſome, I know, that lay all the blame upon the negligence of the Prelates, accuſing them of betraying that care where with they were entruſted for the good of the People; and are therefore urgent to have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> made the firſt examples of Juſtice, as having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> led the Churches with <hi>a company of ſcandalous deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt fellowes,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of honeſt and faithfull Paſtours. But were this true, the evill they complaine of would have ſhewed it ſelfe during their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113221:24"/> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d while theſe monſters were in place, and not onely within theſe few yeares, as it hath done.</p>
            <p>Not would this ſhameleſſe ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umny deſerve any other anſwer, were it not expedient to let the world know, that at the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the peace of the Church was moleſted, the Devill ſhooke off his chaines, and hath ever ſince without all controule diſgorged his venime in the midſt of it.</p>
            <p>So long as there was a perfect harmony of affections betwixt the People and their Paſtours, and an abſolute conformity to thoſe rules which were unanimouſly obſerved for the ſpace of a whole age and upwards; ſuch as had any ſeeds of a corrupt and depraved ſoule, were at leaſt over-awed, and ſo not daring to appeare abroad, they were made uncapable of doing any miſcheife. Thoſe who are beſt acquainted with the Innovations of the times, and that make any conſcience of a Lye, will all conclude with me, that the diſorder which at this day hath overcaſt all <hi>England</hi> with an everlaſting ſhame, owed it's beginning to none but ſuch as have uſurped the place of thoſe ancient Divines and Paſtours which they drive to their Cures. They are for the moſt part but a ſchiſmaticall and factious Crew, which the madneſſe of a brutiſh and ſeditious People hath confuſedly thruſt up into the pulpit: Men of a farre different tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per from thoſe, who were in a peaceable and Legall way preferred to thoſe places before: Such at <hi>Lond.</hi> were <hi>Holdſworth, Hacket, Featley, Marſh, Shoote, Squire,</hi> all men of abilities, and ſuch as the <hi>Puritans</hi> themſelves, before ever theſe troubles began, followed with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Theſe worthy perſons who have by their learning and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation ſo much advanced the Proteſtant cauſe, when to ſatisfy their Conſcience and diſcharge the duty of their callings, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to prevent the growing evils, and to choak the Ieeds of that fatall and deadly diviſion among all the members of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, were ſhamefully debarred of their Liberty, the exerciſe of their profeſſion, and to compleate their miſeries, having firſt made them ſpectatours of ſuch ignorant, malicious and turbulent Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands as were preferred to their Benefices, and poſſeſt of their Houſes, they thruſt them into Dungeons, where they ſtill continue loaded with chaines and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ons, bemoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing their owne and their Countryes miſery. The moſt of the <hi>Cambridge</hi> Doctors have well
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113221:25"/> nigh beene in as bad condition for refuſing to take up armes againſt their Prince.</p>
            <p>Above all Doctor <hi>Ward,</hi> who after he had beene Profeſſour of Divinity in that famous Univerſity for the ſpace of thirty yeares, reputed generally for one of the moſt pious and knowing men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his time, and who had with much vehemence oppoſed <hi>Popery and Arminianiſme,</hi> and all other Innovations of our age, hath ſuffered divers torments by their cruelty, who endeavoured to extort his approbation of that tyranny which they exerciſed upon the Soules of all thoſe they ſought to engage in their faction. In fine, he died, having beene kept in bonds as a vile Malefactour: His laſt words acquaint us ſufficiently with the nature of his crime.—<hi>I will never</hi> (ſaid he, giving up the Ghoſt) <hi>be a Rebell to my King, nor well I ever contribute to that outrage which is done to my Prince.</hi> Thoſe be the <hi>deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes</hi> the Biſhops ſet up; theſe be the <hi>Monſters</hi> whom they chaſe out of their Pulpits, and baniſh the Churches. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which the Parliament, or rather a franticke people, have put in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> roomes, are ſuch as I have formerly deſcrib'd you, who preach no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but injuries, and denounce nothing but curſings; and yet, for all this, talke of agreement with us in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly it highly concernes us to entertaine no manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce or allyance with them.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake onely of the outward conformity; as for that within, what fellowſhip and unity of ſpirit can there be betwixt us a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d thoſe that are enemies to all Order, and harbour ſo many impurities amongſt them? Theſe are they of which your Synods muſt henceforth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, (if the <hi>Independents</hi> doe not quite ſuppreſſe them) and who muſt preſcribe Rules to Chriſtendome. Theſe be they who muſt mould the Diſcipline and diſpoſe of the Government of the Church. Judge now with what wiſedome and holineſſe it is like to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned. Let them ordaine or execute what they pleaſe, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates muſt be no better then Lookers on, in as much as the Clergy and themſelves are two diſtinct bodies, which muſt needs draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it ſuch conſequences as are moſt pernicious both to Church and State; For by this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes a doore is opened not onely to ſedition, tumults, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d civill warres, but even to all exceſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and licentiouſneſſe, to which that Nation is naturally devoted. There
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113221:25"/> would be leſſe cauſe to feare any ſuch diſorder, might the Biſhops be ſtill continued, and enjoy their Priviledge of ſitting in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The People would entertaine better correſpondence one with another, and Peace would ſooner flouriſh amongſt them.</p>
            <p>The Prelates (like faithfull Paſtours) preaching innocency as well by their practiſe as their doctrine, and as members of a Convention repreſenting the whole State, would by their authority nouriſh good agreement and perfect harmony in all the inferiour Clergy. This your Boutefeus and oppoſers of Epiſcopacy perceive well enough; and therefore would have no Rulers at all, neither Biſhop, nor Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. In which reſpect they are farre worſe then the Miniſters of that Tyrant of the Church, who in ſhaking off, as much as in them lieth, all obedience to ſecular Princes, acknowledge a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Heads amongſt themſelves, and by the ſeverall aſcents and power of ſuperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ity, which they call <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> (and which they have prudently eſtabliſhed for prevention of diſcords and confuſion) they arrive at laſt at one, to whom all indifferently are bound to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, as to their ſpirituall Monarch.</p>
            <p>They bragge withall of an intended conformity to <hi>Geneva;</hi> But let me tell them, before they can doe this, they muſt abjure that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependence</hi> which they are ſo hot in purſuit of; and in ſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maſters and Lords Paramount in their Conſiſtories, they muſt ſubmit to their juſt Authority, whom God hath in every State depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to repreſent his Authority, to wit, Princes, and their Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: For ſo it is in <hi>Geneva,</hi> where in the place they iſſue forth their ſpirituall cenſures, one of the <hi>cheife Senatours</hi> is alwaies appointed to paſſe ſentence upon offenders, without the concurrence of any one beſides, which denotes the ſubordination of the Conſiſtory, and it's ſubjection to the Magiſtrate. I inſtance not in this Cuſtome, as if I thought it worthy the imitation: no, it hath it's blemiſhes as well as thoſe in other places, and is perhaps as repugnant to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient practice of the Church. That which I moſt diſlike in it (as a matter of dangerous conſequence) is, that inſtead of the uſuall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline among the Faithfull in winning the Soule from vice by ſweet alluring meanes (after the example of God, who drawes us <hi>with the cords of love)</hi> they exerciſe a temporall Juriſdiction, and practice the ſeverity of Judges meerly ſecular; which begets two evils at once; the firſt, an intrenching upon the Churches function,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113221:26"/> in depriving her of the liberty of cenſuring crimes: The ſecond is, that by the rigour of that Cuſtome Offenders are many times driven to ſuch deſperate reſolutions, that they chuſe rather to flee the City, then to abide the haz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd of a triall; whence commonly ariſeth a third; namely, that by the interceſſion of Parents or Freinds, they are permitted to compound with their purſes, and ſo that repoſe and ſecurity which ſhould be found onely in the goodneſſe of men (ſuch eſpecially as would be accounted <hi>Saints)</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> often to be had in the corruption and venality of the Judges: the ready way to impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and hardneſſe of heart.</p>
            <p>Can they now after all this object againſt the Biſhops of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that either avarice or corruption hath prevailed with them to connive at the vicious, or that they uſed too much rigour and precipitation in the execution of their authority? If ſo be they have any deſigne to make <hi>Geneva</hi> their patterne, For my part I finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing commendable in their Diſcipline, but this; that our firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers have hereby given the world ſufficient proofe of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute averſion from infringing the force of Lawes, or undermining the Authority of the Magiſtrates; And that they never dreamt of being endowed with a power (ſo directly oppoſite to all ſecular authority) which might any way diſoblige them from obedience due to Princes.</p>
            <p>The cuſtome they have in their <hi>monethly Aſſemblies</hi> is yet more for our purpoſe. For beſides that they never conveene without the conſent of their Senatours, either expreſs'd or implyed, (no more then our aſſemblyes doe in <hi>France)</hi> the ſeverall reſults and acts of thoſe meetings are altogether invalid, till the ſame Powers have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and ratified them; which is yet more remarkeable, in as much as there they confine themſelves to the cognition of ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alone, as reflect either upon manners, or Religion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Palatinate</hi> went beyond <hi>Geneva</hi> in this particular, where in the Eccleſiaſticall Aſſembly at <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> the Prince had alwaies his Officers, or <hi>Overſeers,</hi> as I may truly call them: Nor was there ever any Synod held within the verge of his Dominions, where there was not a <hi>Preſident</hi> deputed by Him; and beſides what ever was agreed upon, nothing could be put in execution, till it had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the examination of his Counſell, and received his owne appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, A cuſtome very conformable to the practice of all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ges ſince
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113221:26"/> the infancy of the Church, whenſoever any Councells at all were held, or where there was any Prince, or ſuch as either might or would challenge any intereſt in them.</p>
            <p>Would our Reformers here walke in the ſame Track, they would abate of that inſolence, whereby they maintaine, that <hi>the power they exerciſe is no other then the power of Heaven, nor would</hi> they any longer call their <hi>Conventicles</hi> the <hi>Tribunall,</hi> and their <hi>Cenſures</hi> the <hi>Decrees</hi> of Chriſt. They would talke no more of a right of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ning in deſpight of their Magiſtrates, or Princes: and when they were conveened by their authority, they would attend their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, as neceſſary to the execution of what they had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. And in caſe they were at firſt denyed it, they would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtraight picke a quarrell, and excommunicate them, much leſſe would they dare to depoſe them for any oppoſition whatſoever. They would confine themſelves ſimply to a power over the conſcience, without encroaching upon the civill Magiſtrate, and under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of advanceing piety towards God, and charity towards their neighbour, would no longer abuſe ſuch weake ſilly people, as ſuffer themſelves to be inveigled by the perſons they ſuſteine as Miniſters of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>But we may lawfully conclude, they thinke of nothing leſſe; they have a quarrell with the temporall lawes, and downe they muſt ſooner or later, if this torrent be not maturely oppoſed. They will deſtroy all Legall Parliaments and overturne all ſecular authority.</p>
            <p>This is the miſcheife which all the ſound Members of the preſent Parliament ſhould eagerly ſtruggle with, and not conſent ſo ſlaviſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y (as their manner hath beene) to ſuch things as threaten the whole with inevitable ruine.</p>
            <p>All the care they take and the paines they beſtow here to reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, as they pretend, the freedome of their Votes, the Liberty of the Subject, and the purity of Religion, are indeed but ſo many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to involve themſelves, with all the ancient rights of Church and State in the ſame common deſtruction; the Capitall Enemies thereof inſenſibly gathering ground, and notwithſtanding all their faire pretences, making their party ſo ſtrong, that when the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall have fancyed themſelves at the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>op of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, (thinking now they have pluck'd up all Tyranny and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition by the rootes,) they will finde in the iſſue, that they have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113221:27"/> intangled the State in ſo much confuſion as all the wit of man will never be able to compoſe, There is no Law here, but Arbitrary. What houſe is ſecure? What perſon free? What wiſe man regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? What honeſt man imitated? What vice puniſhed? What virtue rewarded? What ſtranger priviledg'd? What Miniſter of State unviolated, contrary to the Law of Nations? All profeſſions, degrees and qualities, are hudled up together in the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. The People which uſed to receive Lawes, in this generall hurliburly preſcribes them, ignorant, malicious, and giddy headed rabble that it is; it muſt be ſhaping a monſter which the whole world cryes out of; nay, 'tis allready formed. The <hi>London</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out being now the ſole Moderatours to all the Rebellious part of the Kingdome. They have ruin'd the Nobility, deſpoiling them partly of their meanes, and partly of their power. Such of the Peeres as continue ſtill amongſt them, are neither of any account, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Authority. You ſhall have three or foure ſeditious raſcalls of the City, who are of no extraction, no merit, no name, (but what they have purchaſed in traduceing honeſt men, in murthering the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and turning each place that lies within the reach of their fury into a diſconſolate Wilderneſſe) more liſtened to, and draw more abettours after them, then all the Houſe of Lords can do. So that me thinkes I heare ſome interpoſe and ſay, certainely this conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you tell us of, hath nothing but a counterfeit name; and is no more then the ſhadow and empty picture of a true Parliament: things are carryed there with ſo much precipitation and violence, that for any man but to talke of moderation, and to indeavour the recalling of ſome humanity into the mindes of men, is the ready way to be accounted a <hi>Malignant:</hi> and they that have attempted any ſuch matter have beene uſed accordingly: Witneſſe the many Members of Parliament, who being returned thither upon a free E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, according to the Lawes of the Land, have nevertheleſſe beene chaſed thence, ſome by the bare Votes of ſuch as complyed with the popular madneſſe, and others by ſome out-rage or injury done to their perſons. And how many of theſe have for their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and integrity ſate in ſix or ſeven Parliaments with a generall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe? What kinde of People now have they ſubſtituted in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Even ſuch as the lawes of the Realme did ever exclude thence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the knowen inſtruments of malice and fury.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113221:27"/>
            <p>They have not indeed quite ſuppreſſed the Houſe of Peeres, but they have notoriouſly vilified it, in ſo much as they will no longer allow them a ſhare in the publique conſultations. No ſhare I ſay, there being but two or three of the Lords left to their liberty, and that for no other reaſon, but becauſe they combine with the faction. The reſt are forced to ſwimme with the ſtreame, and they have not ſpirit enough to contradict the major part in any thing, though their Conſcience prompt them never ſo much unto it.</p>
            <p>Things could ne'r have come to this paſſe, had not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops beene outed, and therefore (as I informed you before) they begun at them; a peice of the moſt notorious violence and injuſtice that ever was heard of, condemned by all the honeſt men I know, that are acquainted with the Principles of Chriſtianity, and the Lawes of a well-grounded Policy, agreeable to both which they were firſt ſeated in Parliament, and ought to have beene continued there, as the only Pillars to ſupport Order and Uniformity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to hinder the State from falling to peices, eſpecially to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the downefall of Monarchy, all other formes of government be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereſo utterly repugnant to it. But I ground not only upon thoſe advantages which Monarchy enjoyes in their conſervation to worke your diſlike of thoſe that outed them, nor upon the ſole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the whole Church, which was ſo much concerned to keepe them in their places. I ſtand altogether for their perſonall rights, which are as ancient as thoſe of the State, the Biſhops having as ſtrong a title to a place in Parliament, as either the Lords, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. For if with the reſt of the Clergy they make a part of the State (as undenyably they do) who can queſtion their ſhare in the rights of the State? So that to exclude them is to ſet up one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct State in the midſt of another, which is all one as to diſmember and divide the ſame State from it ſelfe, and by conſequent to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage it to its owne inevitable deſtruction. Beſides, as the Nobility and the Clergy (though both concurring) cannot without violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Publique Right exclude the Commons from publike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions where Lawes are to be made for all, ſo neither can the Nobility and Commons (though both agreeing) debarre the Clergy, no more then the Clergy and the Commons can exclude the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
            <p>The caſe being thus, who ſees not, that in the expulſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113221:28"/> all the rights of the State are infringed, &amp; that this is the act of an unruly multitude: which (being empoyſoned with a ſpirit of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniſme) did at the firſt extort the approbation of thoſe Lords that ſtayed amongſt them, and then rewarded their Cowardice with the loſſe of their Power, and reducing them unto ſuch a low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible condition, that they could ſcarce be more vilified were they quite expelled the Houſe.</p>
            <p>Weigh a little (I beſeech you) with what pretences they ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke this outrage. They will needes perſwade us, that <hi>Holy orders are inconſiſtent with ſecular employments,</hi> and that <hi>it is a thing below the Miniſters of the Goſpell to intermeddle in civill Affaires.</hi> To which purpoſe they quote us ſeverall paſſages of Scripture, and urge with all the example of a certaine <hi>Church man,</hi> whom <hi>Cyprian</hi> would not allow any commemoration, becauſe he had taken upon him to be Guardian to a ward. But this rigour which they preſſe ſo hotly upon the Clergy is neither conſequent, nor character of true Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. 'Tis indeed the iſſue of an Anabaptiſticall braine. <hi>Henderſon</hi> and <hi>Marſhall</hi> (two of their moſt able and expert Divines) proclaime to the world by their ſecular employments in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that they make but a mocke of theſe Arguments, and that they beleeve thoſe of their profeſſion may without wounding their conſcience, or transgreſſing the rules of Chriſtianity embrace all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to promote the good of the Church, though it be in the conduct of temporall affaires. They have their generall Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if they had never entered upon holy Orders, by which they are enabled to heare and determine any matter of State, even to the advanceing of a warre.</p>
            <p>But granting theſe men the inconſiſtence they dreame of, would not you concurre with me in this, that though the Biſhops Votes in Parliament be not ſimply neceſſary as a part of the civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet they ought to be granted them as the undenyable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of that univerſall priviledge which all free-borne Subjects en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, which is, not to be bound by any Law they never aſſented to, either in their owne perſons, or by their proxies.</p>
            <p>Beſides it was ever till now thought but reaſon and equity, that to ſuch conventions where both ſpirituall and temporall affaires are to be joyntly agitated, there ſhould be ſummoned not onely your ſecular Sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>-men to judge of the utility, or (as they phraſe it here)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113221:28"/> the convenience of Lawes, nor ſuch onely as are skilfull in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to give verdict of their legality, but withall ſome wiſe and honeſt Divines, to judge for matter of piety in enacting them. The truth is, theſe cavillers bewray both in their ſpeeches and in all their proceedings an abſolute incapacity of any ſound judgement, blindly hurried on to an alteration of government, out of a fond conceite, that their deſigne will ſucceed ſo fortunately as to leade the dance for all the people in <hi>Europe</hi> to follow, to which they ſollici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them in their Covenant. But they have more wit, I trow, then to be their Apes. They have better rules to follow of their owne; eſpecially we Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">When they of <hi>London</hi> were told, that the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous courſes they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooke againſt the Papiſts here, would ſooner or later be practiced upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in <hi>France:</hi> their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, Let others looke to themſelves and let us alone for looking to our ſelves.</note> with whoſe inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s thoſe Gentlemen were very little affected, when they uſed the Papiſts with ſo much inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, ſo as it ſeems they would not acknowledge us for their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or that their charity was very cold towards us.</p>
            <p>We have learned both from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, the Doctors of the Church, and all our firſt Reformers, that ſuch as be Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries either of the Church or State have no portion amongſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, nor the Saints of God; and for this very reaſon I cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded they have any favourers or Abettours amongſt us, or that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to whom God hath given the leaſt graine of underſtanding or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, will not condemne their deſigne, and all their proceedings, and having once adviſed them to quit ſuch courſes, will not utterly deteſt them if they perſevere.</p>
            <p>You will ſay now, that though they have put downe <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and undermined the power of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> yet they are not any way diſaffected to <hi>Royalty.</hi> Can any man beleive this after ſo many thouſand ſeditious Propoſitions, which they daily publiſh both in Preſſe and Pulpit? peruſe them, I beſeech you, for my ſake, though I know you cannot doe it without horrour, and ever and anon turning your eyes from them; ſo full of venime are they againſt all the Princes in the world; ſo contrary to the doctrine and practice of Chriſtians, and ſo injuriuos to the name and profeſſion of all true and ſincere Proteſtants, ſuch are theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Though the King be greater then any one of his Subjects in particular, yet he is farre leſſe then the body collective of all his Subjects: The King is for the people, and not the people for the King; and by conſequent, the people are of more worth and value then he, in as much as the meanes are alwaies ſubordinate to that end to which they are directed, and from whence
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113221:29"/> they derive their worth: The power and authority of any uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tyrant is as much from God, as that of lawfull Kings: The Power of Princes (thoſe eſpecially which by inheritance are ſuch) flowes from the people, and conſequently is more deeply rooted and eminently ſeated in them, then it is in the Perſon of the Prince; becauſe, Quod efficit tale eſt magis tale.</hi> (I am forced to make uſe of their owne bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous tearmes, that I may the better expreſſe the barbarouſneſſe of their conceptions.) <hi>As Kings receive their power from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſo they may be diveſted of it by them, either in the body collective of all, or in the body repreſentative in Parliament, or by the major part of either. In caſe the King ſhall falſifie the Oath he takes at his Coronation, the people are thereupon diſcharged, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d freed from their alleagiance to him;</hi> Poſitions ſo much the more abſurd, becauſe the Lawes of that Land have provided to the contrary, and that all the world have acknowledged it as a maxime, that <hi>the King of England never dyes;</hi> that without all diſtinction of time, as well before as after his Coronation, he receives all ſuch homages and ſervices, as are due to the Crowne; that he is not King upon condition, as if by violation thereof, he ſhould fall from his Right to the Kingdome, but upon bare promiſes, the non performance of which is enough to denominate him unjuſt, but not to depoſe him. They proceed, <hi>No ſonne may with more equity binde the hand of his diſtracted fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no marriner more juſtly remove a Pilot from the Sterne, who would wracke the ſhip (either out of ignorance, or malice) then Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may by force of armes dethrone their Prince, if he ſhall once appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently hearken to any counſels pernicious to the State, and that the Common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wealth either by his weakeneſſe, or negligence, be in danger of ruine. Saint</hi> Paul <hi>doth not command, but barely exhort a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ery ſoule to be ſubject to the higher powers. This was but a prudentiall counſell of one that was to rule a People at ſuch a time as they had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength nor meanes to doe otherwiſe, and that to thinke the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry were to put ſuch a yoake upon the conſcience, as he never dreamed of; By the higher powers Saint</hi> Paul <hi>speakes of, we are not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Perſon of a King, but his charge and office, as it is repreſented in his Courts, and in the Parliament;</hi> inſomuch that the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> according to this doctrine, may beare armes againſt CHARLES STEVVART, reſiding at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and yet ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that alleagiance which is due to the King in his Parliament at
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113221:29"/> 
               <hi>Lond.</hi> Which is as much of a true body to make an idle phantaſme, of a King a <hi>Chimera,</hi> as ſome have done of Chriſt himſelfe, transubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating him from a true man to an imaginary, ſenſeleſſe, and abſurd I know not what. The Authors of theſe pernicious opinions might learne a little more wiſedome, were they but capable of weighing (as they ought) the rules of that State; which informe us that every treaſon reſpects either mediately or immediately the perſon of the King. There can none of them be ignorant, how that before theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall diſtractions, all the Judges were of opinion, and have ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the caſe, that the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> are clearely and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely bound to obey their Prince even in his <hi>naturall capacity,</hi> that is, the perſon of CHARLES STEVVART, and not onely in his <hi>politique capacity,</hi> as he is I know not what imaginary and Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke King. Beſides they need not be informed how this very do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which the Parliamenteers at this day publiſh to the world, and upon which they ground all their ſeverall acts of violence, is both in the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and thoſe acts concerning the baniſHment of <hi>Hugh Spencer,</hi> condemned in full Parliament, and rejected as a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Treaſon, fraud, and Rebellion. They proceed yet further, and tell us. That <hi>the Parliament may in caſe of neceſſity ordaine lawes for peace and warre in spight of the Prince, which ſhall equally oblige every member of the State; And in caſe the King refuſe to confirme them, the ſame Parliament is to be the ſole arbitratour and judge of that neceſſity; and of the time how long it ought or can continue; That the King is bound to ratifie all preſented to him by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, notwithſtanding all the objections which either his Counſell or his owne reaſon and Conſcience ſhall ſuggeſt unto Him. That the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Government ought alwaies to give place to the Eccleſiaſticall.</hi> Were it ſo, that the government of the Church here were partly Democraticall, as the <hi>Browniſts</hi> would have it, or partly Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and partly Democraticall, as it is amongſt the <hi>Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> it is eaſy to inferre, what would become of the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the holy maximes and pious Doctrines of thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to purity of life, and talke of reſtoring the Lawes and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces framed by our firſt Reformers to that vigour and Authority, which the Tyrants of the Conſcience, and enemies of all ſecular po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer have wreſted from them. I am ſure neither <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:113221:30"/> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Peter,</hi> taught them any ſuch leſſon, but <hi>Maria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, Bellarmine, Bourchier, Brutus, Buchanan,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh finebrands employed by the Devill to diſturbe that Order, which the Eternall providence of Heaven had ſet up in the World.</p>
            <p>Let me hereunto adde that notable demonſtration of their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards their Queene. They have expreſſely prohibited all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers both publique and private for Her Converſion. A horrible thing that they ſhould plot the deſtruction of Her ſoule, and endeavour to extend the fruits of their Rebellion againſt Her in another world. Will you not ſay it had beene enough to perſecute Her in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but I have not yet told you all. They have alſo baſely and inſolent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtained Her Reputation, and, in a way which all honeſt men will account no better then <hi>parricide,</hi> attempted to murther <hi>a Princeſſe, a Daughter of France,</hi> to whom the winds and the ſea had ſhewed more pitty but an houre before.</p>
            <p>And yet forſooth they muſt needs have all the Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to make them their Precedent: inviting us, whom they ranke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch <hi>as groane under the yoake of Anti Chriſtian Tyranny, to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> 
               <hi>joine with them in the ſame or like Aſſociation and Covenant,</hi> and to uſe our utmoſt endeavours for the recovery of Peace and quiet in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of Chriſtendome. What is this but to ſollicite us to ſhake off the yoake of Soveraignty? to deny all ſubjection to our Princes, and at once to deſtroy both their Authority and their Perſons? For all which they pretend the <hi>Advancement of the Kingdome of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis indeed mightily advanced ſince theſe men, who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves his Diſciples, have ſubverted all ſecular Authority amongſt them, ſcattering abroad ſuch poſitions as ought to render them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to us, in as much as they convince them before all the Powers of God's eſtabliſHing to be ſowers of ſedition, Libertiniſme, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            <p>But granting them that all this combuſtion they make in the world is to advance the Kingdome of Chriſt; Have they any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the example of the Primitive Chriſtians to purſue that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd by ſuch meanes? no, it was never in their thoughts to arme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo much as againſt thoſe Pagan Monſters, whoſe calmeſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour towards them farre ſurpaſſed in rigour and cruelty all the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113221:30"/> outrage and perſecution which we can be imagined to have ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from any of our Princes, for above five hundred yeares together. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was reprov'd for preſuming to defend his Maſter with the ſword. This example l'me ſure is authentique; nor is that of the Chriſtians under the Emperour <hi>Julia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> much inferiour to it. Their number was great, and their power formidable, but their Religion reſtrained them from employing it againſt their Prince, though in their owne defence. Pleaſe you to call to minde the <hi>Theban Legion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe they had all heard and weighed that injunction of our Saviour; <hi>But I ſay unto you, that ye reſiſt not evill.</hi> They had learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo, that <hi>the Powers are ordained of God, and that whoſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the Power reſiſteth the ordinance of God.</hi> Not as if that prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to reſiſt Princes implyed a Command of obeying them againſt Conſcience. All that can be deduced thence is this, That in caſe they ſhall perſecute their Subjects out of any conſiderations whatſoever, whether ſacred or civill, it were better to endure a thouſand deaths then to lift up a hand againſt them.</p>
            <p>The crime of theſe men will appeare farre more horrid, if notice be taken, that the King againſt whom the combination is made, did never attempt the leaſt innovation either in Religion, or Liberty. I ſpeake onely of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Scotland,</hi> I am not ignorant what hath paſſed there, of which I intend to give you a particular relation.</p>
            <p>They cannot produce any innovation here, Indeed the <note n="a" place="margin">It is to be preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the Author, being a ſtranger, was too faire tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with the vulgar out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this worthy Prelate: whoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pious actions, &amp; the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions had he tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, he would readily have given another character of him. And when he ſhall underſtand and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his conſtant perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to Death in the ſame reſolutions of zeale for the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, and exemplary loyalty to his King, (for which he became a willing ſacrifice) no doubt but he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill be as ready to retract this raſh cenſure, as we to admoniſh.</note> 
               <hi>Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury</hi> was ſhrewdly ſuſpected to have beene contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome. That weake, ill-temperd, and fondly ambitious ſoule, would perhaps have preſumed to be tampering, had he continued longer in place, which is therefore now the principall charge againſt him.</p>
            <p>But as for the King, what ſignall demonſtrations hath he not ever given the world of an extreame a verſion from Popery? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proteſtations hath he made of ſticking cloſe to the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? How carefull is he to performe all thoſe duties to which the Faith he profeſſeth obligeth him? He hath filled the Churches and Sees with men whoſe piety, knowledge, and converſation, are patternes worthy the imitation of the moſt Orthodox Chriſtians.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113221:31"/> His houſe hath ever abounded with men of Learning and Honeſty. Beſides, what would it advantage him to reeſtabliſh Popery? Is he weary of being a free Monarch? Would he do homage againe to <hi>Rome,</hi> and acknowledge a Soveraignty above his owne? The Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of his Crowne as well as thoſe of his Conſcience would not ſuffer him to entertaine ſuch a thought. But this is not all, he would have cauſe to feare a farre greater miſcheife from <hi>Scotland,</hi> which all the advantages he could hope for from all the Papiſts in the world would never be able to counterpoiſe. He muſt further ſhake off them of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and in doing that, forfeit all his reputation in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> He muſt breake with <hi>Denmarke;</hi> Nay he muſt not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any commerce, either with his neareſt allyes, <hi>or his deareſt freinds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The marrying of his Daughter to the Prince of <hi>Orange's</hi> Sonne, is a pregnant evidence of his affection to the Proteſtant Religion. But to make good their Calumny, they accuſe him of favouring Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; and yet who knowes not, that the exchequer was never fuller with their compoſition-money, then now? In the Reignes of King <hi>Edward,</hi> Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> they were not uſed with halfe the rigour. When this King ſhewed them moſt favour it came ſhort of what they have done. But I pray, by what princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſtianity are we bound to deſtroy ſuch as are of a different Religion? There is no forceing of any man's beleife, none that can ſubdue the Liberty of the ſoule, God onely excepted. Our French Kings are well inſtructed in this point, they might with a like equity deſtroy or baniſh us, as here they do Papiſts, did they not know that the conſcience neither can nor ought to be forced. Moſt true it is, that the Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> never attempted any thing upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Princes, what violence ſoever hath beene practic'd upon them by ſuch as abuſed their Authority; on the contrary for all their ſufferings they have made it legible to the world, that they would rather part with all the bloud in their veines in their defence, then hazard the leaſt drop to be revenged of them, even then when ſome ſtrange counſells had prevailed with them to ſigne their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. A very preſſing conſideration wherewith to refute all pretended intereſts of Religion, and to procure them a toleration, notwithſtanding the differences of opinions. The Papiſts caſe in <hi>England</hi> is much unlike theirs, in as much as they are ever and a non
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113221:31"/> plotting the deſtruction of their Prince; a crime I am ſo farre from excuſing, that I deteſt it as one of the moſt execrable which the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake-hell in the world can be guilty of. But withall let me adde, that it had never beene ſo much in uſe, had thoſe, who could not conforme to the Reformation, beene dealt with more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably. The Law here is unjuſt onely in condemning their perſons to death, as ſuch, but juſt in proceeding againſt their treaſonable machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. Let it in God's name have its full courſe upon them as they are Traitours, but not barely as miſ-beleevers. God gave to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles no Commiſſion to propagate the Goſpell of his ſonne by force of Armes; much leſſe to our States and Kingdomes now: would but Chriſtians lay this ſeriouſly to heart, they would never make uſe of any but the <hi>Armes of the ſpirit</hi> againſt thoſe that are reprobate to the truth; and ſo there would be ſome difference made betwixt Papiſts that are onely offenders againſt God, and ſuch as are ſo both againſt God and the Princes which he hath ſet over them. How many of them beare as much reſpect to their Soveraignes as we can poſſibly do to ours, and are as zealous for the good of Kingdomes and the Peace of People? Others indeed there be that have ſucked the ſame venime with theſe new emiſſaries of Hell, who take this for a <hi>Maxime: That Kings are no longer Kings, but reall Tyrants, when they ceaſe to be Catholiques; and that it is a meritorious Act to embrew their bands in their bloud, and to free the People from their dominion over them.</hi> Let the Law be executed againſt ſuch without mercy, not let any Princes or States give the leaſt toleration to ſuch abhominable Incendiaries. But as for the reſt, let the unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble converſation and integrity of thoſe that are in authority over them, preach a Reformation to them, untill their houre be come, and grace from Heaven be ſhed amongſt them. If the Religion they profeſſe be not of it ſelfe deſtructive, and that in all other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they ſubmit to the Lawes and maintaine the Intereſts of the State in which they live, all the power which can be challenged over them, is but to reſtraine them within the publique rules: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an act of the greateſt injuſtice, to deprive them either of their lives or eſtates, for no other reaſon but becauſe they are incapable of the knowledge and piety of another perſon. This was one of the wormes that gnawed upon the conſcience of <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, that he had attempted by force of Armes to propagate Chriſtianity
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113221:32"/> in the new world, where the Devill was their only deity. And how heavy ſhould this example lye upon the Conſciences of all ſuch Princes and Magiſtrates as exerciſe the ſame cruelties upon their Subjects, or on thoſe that differ not in the foundation from them, worſhipping the ſame Chriſt, acknowleding him to be what he is, and all expecting ſalvation by him?</p>
            <p>But if ſuch preſſing motives cannot worke upon <hi>England,</hi> let them at leaſt conſider what muſt neceſſarily befall to many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand honeſt Proteſtants that live under the dominion of Popiſh Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who certainely will revenge upon them all the outrage done the Papiſts under Proteſtant Princes. And the number of the former is farre greater, then the number of theſe; ſo that for one Preiſt who out of a fond diſtemper'd zeale ſhall be put to death here, there will be in other places f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty Proteſtant Miniſters in danger to periſh. Beſides this, <hi>France</hi> at the firſt led the way in abſtaining from all cruelty towards thoſe of the Reformation there; but was afterwards implacably mad againſt them neare upon the time that thoſe rigorous Lawes were enacted againſt <hi>Recuſants</hi> in this Kingdome. And if in <hi>France</hi> ſuch courſes were thought fit to be utterly abandoned, why ſhould they be continued in <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If none of theſe conſiderations will move them, let them forbeare at leaſt out of charity to us. And to this purpoſe they may recall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their memories what <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Theoderick</hi> did in the caſe of the <hi>Catholiques</hi> and the <hi>Arians.</hi> The former vehemently perſecuted the <hi>Arians</hi> in all quarters of his Dominions, and the latter did as much to the <hi>Catholiques</hi> in the Weſt, where he commanded. But both at laſt were content to ſuperſede from bloudſhed, and by the adviſe of their Doctours, in the yeare 525 (If I miſtake not) allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them caſe and liberty of Conſcience, whom they could not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by torments and violence. <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was one that interpoſed in the buſineſſe, and the firſt who perſwaded the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Prince to more mildneſſe, and to quit all thoughts of rigour and courſes of cruelty. The Chriſtians of thoſe times judged aright, that violence did not ſuit with the Goſpell, and that ſteele was no fit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to make impreſſion upon obdurate hearts. And though their Princes would ſomtimes arme them againſt <hi>Pagans</hi> or <hi>Soctaries,</hi> it was meerely for the intereſts and ſafety of their Crownes; as in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that <hi>Juſtine,</hi> I named you, when he ſaw the Empire ready to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113221:32"/> fall in peices, and that the moſt warlike nations (who had ſubdued the reſt) were fallen off to ſuch Princes, as indeed bore the name of Chriſtians, but were by reaſon of their Hereticall opinions divided from them, had great reaſon to be afraid that many of his owne Subjects agreeing with them in the ſame Principles, would follow their example. It concerned him not to deſtroy them, and to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour them neare himſelfe was to nouriſh ſo many vipers in his owne boſome. Yet in as much as he was the occaſion that many <hi>Orthodox</hi> Chriſtians loſt their lives, and becauſe he had no juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over the Conſciences of thoſe that were not ſuch, he relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed all former courſes of violence and perſecution. 'Twere well, if this example could worke the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and all other Princes in the world to the like moderation. Do not even the <hi>Turk</hi> and the <hi>Perſian</hi> tolerate us in their Dominions? Shall humanity be found in <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and not in Chriſtian and civilized Princes? What? doth the Reformation oblige us to be cruell? I cannot thinke it, no more then that any Proteſtant in <hi>France</hi> (who hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd his reaſon) will not ſubſcribe with me to the ſame opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not this to diſſwade from the uſe of ſuch meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neceſſary for aboliſhing of Superſtition, and reeſtabliſHing the purity of Chriſtian Religion. There be other courſes enough beſides vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to reduce ſtragglers into the way. And if there were not, ſhould they finde a toleration, might they not be prevented from ſeducing others? If there be any juſt cauſe to feare the conſequents of the <hi>Maximes</hi> and Doctrines they maintaine, it concernes the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate prudently to provide a remedy, and to ſtop them from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding further; but above all to take care that their Prieſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>atter not any rebellious Doctrine, a thing very familiar with ſuch as have had their breeding at <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> or in any Schooles of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites.</hi> Had they their education at home, they would breath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but affection to the place of their nativity; and the liberty which would be indulged them among their Parents and kindred (without the leaſt jealouſie of ſuffering for any differences in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) would nouriſh reſpect in them towards their King and all other their Superiours; whereas rigour doth but harden them the more, and imbolden them to redeeme themſelves at any rate from that irkeſome neceſſity (which is commonly impoſed on them) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113221:33"/> otherwiſe then they will, and perhaps too then they can.</p>
            <p>Let me but adde a word of the <hi>Liberties</hi> they talke of, and for which they make ſo much noyſe in the world. I am not altogether ignorant what they be, as having ſeene a great part of the Lawes and Cuſtomes of that Kingdome. Certainely thoſe gentlemen may with much credit charge their King with the violation of them, who have themſelves ſo inſolently trampled upon whatſoever hath the face either of Publique or private right. I ſhall attend an opportunity to give you a diſtinct information of their baſeneſſe in this particular. For the preſent I ſhall onely aſſure you thus much in generall; that their complaints are moſt groundleſſe, as flowing from the ſame ſpirit by whoſe inſtigation they have ſlandered the religion and piety of their Prince. Did he ever during that peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able part of his reigne over them, endeavour to ſtretch his prerog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or to protect any of his Creatures, that encroached, I will not ſay upon the Lawes of the Realme, but even upon the propriety of the meaneſt Subject? Was there ever in any Kings Reigne knowne fewer eſcheats, except thoſe from Recuſants? or fewer proſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and baniſhments? fewer executions? leſſe diſorder and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence? leſſe repining? fewer impoſitions? in a word, fewer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations? And therefore it concerned them to fancy (as they have done) a thouſand illegall and tyrannicall actions in that Prince, that ſo they might more eaſily delude the People; and in the iſſue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage them (as in their owne defence) to a reſolution of making head againſt him, either wholly to deveſt him of all rule, or to reigne a while in his ſtead, or at leaſt to have a conſtant ſhare with him in the government. That blinde unruly <hi>Beaſt</hi> is never more ſervilely tame, then when abuſed with lyes, ever repining and ready to mutine at any extraordinary impoſition, though never ſo reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and advantagious: You may lead it whither you pleaſe with a ſpecious pretence; ſo willing at this time to ſacrifice it ſelfe to the ambition of ſome factious ſpirits, intoxicated by their oaths and proteſtations, that they aime at nothing but the good of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. In like manner have the Peſantry of <hi>France</hi> ſometimes incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderately engaged themſelves in the ſervice of a King of <hi>Navarr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> a Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and another of <hi>Burgogne,</hi> who having in effect no other deſigne then to advance their owne greatneſſe, would
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113221:33"/> notwithſtanding have nothing more in their mouthes then the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique liberty, of which (to ſpeake truth) they were the moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious if not the onely enemies. Juſt ſo it is here now. They that have undertaken the protection of Priviledge, poſſeſſing their abettours and Diſciples with the hopes of ſecuring their liberties, thinke of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then the intereſts of others; and that very thing which they pretend to appeare in the feild for, hath beene more violated and infringed by them, then ever it was by all the Kings of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet they have ſo varniſht over their actions, that by this trick they have got the eſtates, the lives, the hearts, nay and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to boot of the People here, wholly into their owne diſpoſall. It may be thoſe unfortunate Wretches will be one day ſenſible of the Impoſture, and perceive at laſt how they have approved and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged themſelves to what will be their deſtruction, if they repent not. For thoſe that flatter them with the hopes of <hi>liberty,</hi> will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther get the upper hand, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them their vaſſals, or elſe plunge them into a condition farre more intolerable then the moſt irkſome ſlavery: were it not for that Anabaptiſticall venime, which hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixed it ſelfe with the naturall propenſion of this people to Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertiniſme, there might be ſome hopes of remedy. But there have been the like diſorders here to fore in this Kingdom. And a man would thinke that the ſoules of the Earle of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> had by a kind of tranſmigration poſſeſſed the ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this preſent Rebellion. But the former were ſo much the more excuſable, in that they made not Religion the ſcreene to their Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſooner put on end to thoſe troubles.</p>
            <p>That you may the better remember the cheife circumſtances of that Hiſtory, give me leave to acquaint you how in the reigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third there was a Parliament held at <hi>Oxford,</hi> which Poſterity juſtly branded with an infamous name, calling it. <hi>The mad Parliament.</hi> (except me but the generall ſuperſtition of thoſe times, and it will mervailouſly reſemble that at <hi>Weſtminſter)</hi> At which time the Lords and Commons fore'd that King to conſent to the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of certaine perſons amongſt them, whom they ſtiled <hi>Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners</hi> and <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of the Peace.</hi> Whereupon under pretence of that extraordinary power, and by vertue not onely of an Ordinance of the two Houſes, but of a compleate Act of Parliament, they roſe up in Armes againſt their Prince, and moleſted him with a long and bloudy Warre, like this.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:113221:34"/>
            <p>After the various ſucceſſe of which inſolent attempt, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall innovations which diſtracted the Kingdome, the review of the whole buſineſſe was committed to a free Parliament, in which the Authors and Promoters of that warre were condemned of High Treaſon, and all the Rebels Eſtates by a ſolemne Act confiſcate. But the extent of the crime abated of the puniſhment, leſt otherwiſe the greateſt part of <hi>England</hi> ſhould have beene made a deſolation. And certainly were there any hopes of a free Parliament now, the trai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous attempt of thoſe who make up that ſhadow of a Parliament, would be proceeded againſt with all rigour, and the example of that at <hi>Oxford</hi> be renewed, ſeeing they have dared to renew the cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. And were the puniſhment proportion'd to the offence, theſe men ſhould be uſed with more ſeverity then the other, they have ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out-done them. For their attempt was onely againſt their owne Prince, but the deſigne of theſe againſt all the Princes in the World. They were contented to be Rebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> themſelves, but theſe muſt have all the Proteſtants in Chriſtendome to be ſo likewiſe. They medl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not with Religion, nor thought to diſquiet the Church; theſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> violated Religion, and torne the Church in peeces. They offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> violence to any of the three States in Parliament, ſuppreſſing onely the votes of ſome particular perſons which croſſed their deſigne. Theſe have outed the whole Body of the Clergy, chaſed away di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Peeres, deſpoiled others of their Eſtates and Authority, ſparing none but ſuch as will be then Fellow-traitours. In breife, the former indeed advanc'd their Rebellion under a pretence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> maintaining the publique Liberties, but they expoſ'd not all the Kings that were to ſucceed to the madneſſe and cruelty of the People, as theſe men doe.</p>
            <p>I know you have often ſeene divers of their Poſitions, but I have reſerv'd one to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is worſe then all the reſt. They maintaine. That <hi>Subjects may in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſuanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of their Liberty take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Armes and employ all their ſtrength againſt any that ſhall endeavour is reduce them to ſlavery. That there is no yoake of which they may not lawfully rid themſelves, whoſoever impoſed it, whether ſome Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, or their owne naturall Prince. That nature it ſelfe dictates unto the whole world the recovery of it's loſt liberty, notwithſtanding any former contracts, or any lawes to which they have ſworue obedience, or even the expreſſe approbation of ſome preceding ages. That whoſoever ſhall have
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113221:34"/> power enough and not employ it to that end, men ſhould be ſo farre from ſtartling at their back rardneſſe, that on the contrary they are to hold them for no other then Rebels againſt that nature, which commands them to dispenſe in this caſe with all former obligations whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, were not this ground enough for all the Magiſtrates in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe to arme againſt ſuch <hi>Peſts</hi> as theſe? You will now reſt fully ſatisfied, that 'tis not Religion they fight for, and that by the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of thoſe <hi>Priviledges</hi> they talke of, they intend nothing but the ruine and deſtruction of ſuch as are in Authority over them. What elſe can we expect from ſuch maximes? They who complaine ſo much of abuſing Monarchy have infringed all the rights of it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. There was a Parliament in <hi>Scotland</hi> held in deſpight of the King, and the Acts of it are daily put in execution, contrary to his expreſſe commands, which is utterly to aboliſh all Regall Power, and to annihilate the Fundamentall Lawes of the State. This Parliament in <hi>England</hi> was indeed conveencd by his Authority, but they bound his hands from diſſolving it when he ought and would have done. No ſooner were the Members met, but he was chaſed from <hi>London,</hi> and they upon this poſſeſſe themſelves of the Houſes, Forts, Caſtles, Ports, Navy and Ammunition of their Prince. They put the Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> to Death upon pretences of their owne deviſing, that ſo they might have ſome colour for the deſigne againſt the perſon of their Soveraigne. They have forced his conſent to an Act, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringeth all the prerogatives of the Crowne. They will needs have the diſpoſall and ordering of his family, murther his friends and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Miniſters, and ſo hinder all from being ſuch. They will clip his Revenues as they pleaſe, not ſuffer him to diſpoſe of vacant offices. They will not allow him any power in Church-affaires; bereave him of his Biſhops, that ſo they may render him uncapable of diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all factious contrivances under colour of Religion; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of all meanes to prevent the execution of them. At this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry preſent they are conſulting how to deprive him of his Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, which you know is one of the faireſt <hi>Flowers</hi> of the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and the moſt proper character of Soveraignty.</p>
            <p>I have almoſt ſpent my ſelfe in limning you the deſignes and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of theſe men; but I hope you will not be weary in peruſing and weighing them. I have beſides many things of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:113221:35"/> to tell you, which I reſerve for ſome better opportunity, when I may have more leiſure and liberty then is allowed me at this preſent.</p>
            <p>In the interim let me earneſtly requeſt you to make what uſe you can of the truth of this Relation in behalfe of Reaſon and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>In God's name employ your utmoſt endeavours to blaſt thoſe falſe pretences of Zeale and Religion, that none of ours be carried away with them. I beleive it was to that end you deſired this Letter from me, which I have diſpatched towards you in perſuance of your commands, and withall to ſatisfy my Conſcience.</p>
            <p>I will ſay nothing what is like to be the ſucceſſe of our Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour here. You may eaſily gueſſe by this Relation. The <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> have as weake hopes, as we: and I'me confident both of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire to teſtify unto the world their love and inclination to Peace although ſome accuſe them of an averſoneſſe from it, and that all their deſignes tend to the nouriſhing of this Warre. But certainly they deſire to ſee and end of it, were it but for this reaſon, that the King of <hi>England</hi> might engage himſelfe in the intereſts of <hi>Germany,</hi> and employ his ſtrength there in behalfe of all the <hi>oppreſſed Princes,</hi> thoſe eſpecially which are more neare unto him. I will diſcourſe with you more at large upon this, when I ſhall have the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to give you an account of thoſe other paſſages mentioned in your Letter.</p>
            <p>In this and all things elſe you ſhall reade the conſtant deſire I have to aſſure you, that I am unfeinedly.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 22. 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt affectionate Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
